<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrines and principles the persecution, imprisonment, banishment, excommunicating of the saints of God, by the priests and magistrates of Scotland, contrary to the doctrine of Christ and the Apostles ...</title>
            <author>Stockdale, William, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5693A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184702</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504530</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504530</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2594:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrines and principles the persecution, imprisonment, banishment, excommunicating of the saints of God, by the priests and magistrates of Scotland, contrary to the doctrine of Christ and the Apostles ...</title>
                  <author>Stockdale, William, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 86 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Will. Stockdale.</note>
                  <note>"George Weare, William Grey, William Mitchell, John Hart, William Stockdale, Richard Ismead."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Persecutions --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171845:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINES AND PRINCIPLES: THE Perſecution, Impriſonment, Baniſhment, Excommunicating of the Saints of God, By the Prieſts and Magiſtrates of SCOTLAND, Contrary to the Doctrine of CHRIST and the APOSTLES.</p>
            <p>Here all may ſee, The <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and their Church, and their Perſecution, Impriſonment and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and Excommunicating of the Saints, and Lambs, Servants, and Children of God, which the Lord moved to go amongſt them, to viſit the Seed of God, in that dark wilderneſs-country, who has been as Sheep among Wolves.</p>
            <p>Alſo, How pure Religion is turned upſide-down, and vain Religion got in its place. And the pure Doctrine of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, which ſaith, Entertain Strangers, Love Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies is loſt amongſt you; In ſtead of entertaining ſtrangers, and loving of enemies, they Impriſon and Perſecute, and have made their Church unſavory: And the Teachers fruits declares to be falſe, who are wreſtlers againſt flesh and blood, and ſtrikers at creatures, which Chriſt and the Apoſtles did not.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Weare</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Hart</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Grey</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Stockdale</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Mitchell</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richard Iſmead</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the Signe of the Black-ſpread-Eagle and winde-Mill in <hi>Martins</hi>-lane near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171845:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171845:2"/>
            <head>THE DOCTRINES AND PRINCIPLES Of the Prieſts of Scotland, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>FIRST, Theſe Presbyterian Prieſts of <hi>Scotland</hi> which Excommunicate and puts out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouges, knowes not the Father and the Son, <hi>John</hi> 16. ſo no true Chriſtians; for how can they be true Chriſtians that knows not the Son of God, nor the Father?</p>
            <p>Secondly, They are no Miniſters of Chriſt; for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>When they curſe, bleſſe ye;</hi> ſo they be out of Chriſts doctrine and teaching, not bleſſing, but curſing, and giving forth curſes, and all the people muſt ſay Amen to their Curſes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They be out of the Apoſtles doctrine, who ſaith, <hi>Bleſſe, and curſe not,</hi> Rom. 12.14. ſo are no Miniſters of Chriſt that curſeth, and gives forth their Curſes to the people to ſay Amen to them: and here they are ſhut out of the Apoſtles doctrine, and Chriſts, all people mark, and take notice, them they are that curſe, which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Bleſſe, and curſe not;</hi> theſe are the Curſers, and not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171845:3"/>Bleſſers, that Excommunicate you out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hugh Archball,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Stravan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Hume,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mahagow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Hambleton,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Glasford</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>James Durram</hi> prieſt of <hi>Glaſgow</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Caſtaires,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Glagow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Francis Ard,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Diſcert.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Matthew Mackel,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Bothwel</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Foreſide,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Lingiah</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>James Neſmith,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Hambleton</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Semple,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Loſmahagow</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Garony,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Edenbrough.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Burnet,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Kilbroid</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſhort Relation of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt ſufferings of the People of God, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> by thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable curſing Prieſts, who covet after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood, as the Reader may finde in this enſuing Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WILL. OSB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE</hi> was Excommunicated by <hi>William Sterling</hi> Prieſt, becauſe he gave his teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt him, and the reſt of the Prieſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Margaret Hambleton</hi> was Excommunicated by <hi>Lewis Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merell,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>New-monkeland,</hi> for entertaining the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the denying the tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call power of the Presbitery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Hutchiſon</hi> was Excommunicated by <hi>James Neſmith,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Hambleton,</hi> and the Prieſt would not give him any account for what he did it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Weare</hi> was Ecommunicated by <hi>John Hume,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Leſmahagow,</hi> and the reſt of the Presbytery of <hi>Lenarick,</hi> for entertaining the people of God called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171845:3"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Michel, John Michel, Robert Todd, Mary Ingliſh, Elizabeth Lappy, Marian Michel:</hi> theſe were Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by <hi>Peter Kid,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Douglaſs,</hi> and the reſt of the Presbytery of <hi>Lenarick,</hi> for denying that <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi> was the Goſpel, they witneſſing the Power of God to be the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Jacke, Gabriel Hood, James Cooke, Gavine Sceven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, John Hambleton, Alexander Hambleton, Jannett Hamble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Barbarah Hambleton, Jannett Hambleton, Andrew Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleton, Jane Hambleton, Katherine Hambleton, Katherine Hart, John Allene, James Hambleton, William Hambleton, Margaret Hambleton, John Hart, James Actkine, John Hart, Alexander Hart, Jean Hart, Gavine Hart, John Lacoke, Jannett Brown, Jeanet Hambleton, Andrew Brown, Jean Brown; Thomas Craiqqe, John Torrens, Katherina Hambleton, Katherina Weare, Jeanet Weare:</hi> Theſe were Excommunicated by <hi>Matthew Mackell,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Bothwell,</hi> and the reſt of the Presbitery at <hi>Hambleton,</hi> for ſaying that Prieſts that preacheth up Sin for terme of life, be Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the man of Sinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Finly, William Gray,</hi> and many others have been Excommunicated by thoſe Prieſts in that manner.</p>
               <p>And after thoſe Prieſts had Excommunicated theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid perſons, they cauſed a general Synode to meet at <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> and made an Order, and publiſhed it in all their Maſſe-houſes, that none of thoſe people called <hi>Quakers</hi> ſhould have any entertainment, and that no people ſhould have any dealing with them in any Civil affaires, not to give curſed men work (as they ſtyled our Friends) and hindring men to work for them, and that under pain of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication; the extent of which Order, is that they ſhould neither buy nor ſell, eat, nor drink with them in the Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stockdale,</hi> and <hi>John Boweram,</hi> being moved of the Lord to go to <hi>Strahavan</hi> in <hi>Evandale,</hi> and declaring the word of truth there one a Market-day to the people, was oftentimes knockt down with ſtones, and ſtoned out of the town with violence by the wicked people.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171845:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stockdale, John Gill,</hi> and ſeveral others having a Meeting in <hi>Strahavan,</hi> a company of the Prieſts hearers came, and fell upon them with ſtaves and ſtones, broke up their Meeting, and ſtoned them above a quarter of a mile out of the town, inſomuch that ſome bloud was ſpilt, and many were ſore bruiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stockdale</hi> was knockt down in the Steeple-houſe yard of <hi>Damanoy,</hi> and the people ſet their feet upon him, and pulled much hair off his head; inſomuch that ſome of them cried he is kild, for he could not ſpeak, nor riſe off the ground for along time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Weare,</hi> and ſeveral others had their Bonnets taken away from them at a Meeting, and they laid it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>William Lowery,</hi> called Juſtice; but he inſtead of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Juſtice, threatned them, ſaying, <hi>If they went to that place to meet again, he would have them whipt, or elſe he would whip them himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Gollon,</hi> Bayliff of <hi>Leanarick,</hi> took away <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Michels</hi> Bonnet by order of <hi>William Jacke,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Carlooke;</hi> and the Prieſt would not let him have it again, neither would he let the ſaid <hi>William,</hi> and ſome others ſtay in the Town all night, although the night was ſtormy, and the Prieſt and the Bayliff had his Bonnet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary Ingliſh,</hi> for going to ask <hi>Peter Kid,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs,</hi> why he warned them to the Seſſions, and did not appear to accuſe them there, was ſhamefully abuſed, and beaten by the Prieſts wife and others: here's the Prieſts fruits.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Fox</hi> the yonger, <hi>Elexander Parker,</hi> and others, had their letters taken from them, and broke up by <hi>George Monk,</hi> and the <hi>Council of Scotland,</hi> and never returned to them again; alſo ten pounds worth of true books taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the people of God called Quakers, by <hi>George Monk,</hi> and the Councell of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and never was given back to this day, it being two years ſince.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander Parker</hi> was caſt in Priſon by order of <hi>George Monk,</hi> and the Councell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Fox</hi> the younger baniſhed, and ſent from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171845:4"/>to Conſtable, by order of <hi>George Monke</hi> and the Councell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Wilſon, George Fox</hi> the younger, and <hi>Richard Iſmead,</hi> was baniſhed from the Iſles of <hi>Orkney</hi> by <hi>George Monks</hi> Comand, and the reſt of the Councel of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander Parker,</hi> and ſeverall others were comanded and ſent out of <hi>Scotland</hi> by <hi>George Monke,</hi> and the order of the Councell of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Howgill, Thomas Robbinſon,</hi> and one more were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended at <hi>Dumfreize</hi> by the ſouldiers and magiſtrates of the town, whereupon the ſaid Souldiers rifled them, and their Port-mantles for Letters, but when they could not finde any to accuſe them withall, the Magiſtrates caſt them into priſon as Vagrants, and did intend to have ſent them into <hi>England</hi> again by Conſtables, but it being proved that they were no Vagabonds, the Magiſtrates and Souldiers was faine to let them go, after all the wrong they had done them, though it was to their own ſhame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtopher Fell</hi> was put into priſon in <hi>Parſley</hi> for ſpeaking to the Prieſt after the Prieſt had done, and the people did threaten that if any Quakers did come again to their Church (as they called it) they would carry knives with them to ſtab them, to which threatning <hi>John Dove,</hi> who was then Lieftenant of a Troop of Horſe, and quartered in that town, ſaid, If they did do as they ſaid, he would bring the Troop of Horſe, and be-ſet them in their houſe, ſo to preſerve the peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Holmes,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his wife, was ſhamefully abuſed in ſeverall places in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Pinder</hi> was put in priſon four dayes, and in the Stocks five houres, and baniſhed out of the Land, for ſpeaking to the people in the Steeple-houſ-yard of <hi>Kilbryde,</hi> between the Prieſts Sermon time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Iſmead</hi> for bidding <hi>James Neſmith</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleton</hi> prove himſelf to be a Miniſter of Chriſt, was put in priſon there, and from thence ſent priſoner to <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> there put in the ſtooks with a gagg in his Mouth, and a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per pinnd on his breſt, and was commanded to depart the Land.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:171845:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stockdall,</hi> was put in priſon four dayes in a hole where he could ſcarce get room to lye down, for ſpeaking to <hi>James Neſmith,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Hambleton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Lancheſter,</hi> and others was ſeverall times put in priſon for ſpeaking in the ſtreets of <hi>Hambleton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Hart, Andrew Browne,</hi> and <hi>John Lacoke,</hi> was impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned ſeverall weeks in <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> for going to the Prieſts houſe to ſpeake to him, and the prieſt, excommunicated them in the mean while.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Jack,</hi> was put in priſon ſome dayes for going to the prieſt to aske why he would excommunicate him, the ſaid <hi>Thomas Jack</hi> was put in priſon, and kept from his Trade, he being a poore man, and his wife lying in Child-bed:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Lancheſter,</hi> and <hi>Robert Withers</hi> was baniſhed out of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Were,</hi> was put in priſon twenty three dayes, and nothing laid to his charge juſtly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Will. Michell,</hi> was put in priſon above twenty nine days for taking a wife contrary to the Prieſts will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Robberton</hi> called Lord of <hi>Ornock</hi> publikely refuſed to enter <hi>Andrew Hambleton</hi> in <hi>Shawton</hi> Hill in his proſſeſſion under him, becauſe he was excommunicated by the Prieſt, wittneſſes of this, <hi>Alexander Hambleton, John Strandders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Gray, James Finly, Robert Gray, Robert Smally, John Robbins,</hi> all five were put in priſon becauſe they could not break Chriſts command.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Hart,</hi> and <hi>Jeannett Browne,</hi> was put into priſon for entertaining the people of God called Quakers.</p>
               <p>Three taken out of an Inn by force in the night ſeaſon, between the tenth and eleventh houre, and ſtoned out of the Town: theſe and many more whoſe names are not here written have ſuffred much by this perſecuting generation of Prieſts, whoſe throates are open ſepulchers to ſwallow down the bloud of the Saints, and Servants of the moſt high God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171845:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Hugh Archballs</hi> Doctrine and Principles, Prieſt of <hi>Stravan</hi> in <hi>Evendale,</hi> Theſe are his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as follow.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr: THat Chriſt hath not enlightened every one that comes into the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Which is contrary to <hi>Johns</hi> doctrine <hi>John</hi> 1.9:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. That Chriſt doth enlighten none but thoſe that do receive him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Contrary to <hi>John</hi> 3: ſpeaking of them which hath the light, and are enlightened, and will not come to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the light will reprove them; ſo he that hates the light is enlightened, and will not receive Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr: That it is blaſphemy to ſay, that the true light doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten and condemn the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Contrary to <hi>John</hi> 1:9: and 3:19: <hi>that ſaith,</hi> This is the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world. And this is the Condemnation of the world, that light is come into the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr: To ſay, that which reproves for ſin is from Heaven, is blaſphemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Contrary to <hi>John</hi> 16:8: which ſaith it is the ſpirit that reproves, which comes from the Father, and the Son, which is from Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. He cryeth up a naturall light, as Sun, Moon, and Stars, and the light of Chriſt was before theſe was made,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>it is blaſphemy to ſay, they that did the things contayned in the Law was bleſſed in the deed, and the Apoſtle ſaid the doers of the Law was juſtified;</hi> and ſaid <hi>he would leave the Friends that ſpeake to him, to the mercy of the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Upon which they ſtruck bitterly with books, fiſts, and ſtones, to deſtroy, but that ſame moderate people and Souldiers ſtayed the Perſecution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:171845:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>John Hume,</hi> Prieſts of <hi>Leſmahagow,</hi> His Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as followes, who got into a Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and ſhut the door upon him; thus he taught the people.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr: THat which was to be known of God, was manifeſt by the things that are created.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Contrary to the Apoſtles doctrine, <hi>Rom:</hi> 1:19: For whatſoever may he known of God is manifeſt in them, for the inviſible things of him from the Creation of the world, are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternal power and God-head, ſo that they are without excuſe: So with that of God in them they know the inviſible things from the foundation of the world and with that they ſee the God-head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr: That God was to be known by the things that were made, as the Sun, Moon, and Stars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> But Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Mat:</hi> 11:27: No man knowes the Father but the Son, and he to whomſoever the Son will reveal him, and the heathens know not God, nor the <hi>Jewes</hi> had not ſeen his ſhape. And his ſervants and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did throw water, ſtones and lime, and perſecuted, and dirtted, and abuſed the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and threw a pan full of water in a Souldiers neck, and the ſaid Prieſt never reproved them; and theſe be the fruits of him, and his own Family, in ſtead of gravity: well may the whole Pariſh be out of order, when his own Family is thus. So he is one that is reproved by the Apoſtles doctrine. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. which ſaith, If you cannot rule your own Family, how can you take care for the Church of God?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171845:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Henry Foreſide,</hi> Prieſt of the Pariſh of <hi>Lingee</hi> in <hi>Dunbarton-ſhire,</hi> ſaid in his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the People.</head>
               <p>Pr. <hi>IF they had any Chriſtian zeal, they would ſtone them whom they call</hi> Quakers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is the blind zeal that ſtones, not the Chriſtian zeale, that have the life of Chriſt; for the Chriſtian zeal is to pray for them that perſecute, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. and not to ſtone them, and to love enemies: it was the <hi>Jewes</hi> zeal that took up ſtones to ſtone Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 8.59. they ſtoned <hi>Steven, Acts</hi> 7.5, 8. and ſtoned the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.19. In this the <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> have proved their Chriſtianity to be out of Chriſt and the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>If Paul and the reſt of the Apoſtles had been alive, they would have ſtoned the</hi> Quakers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here all may ſee his work to be the envious man in <hi>Cains</hi> way, <hi>Jude</hi> 11. who would murther, and wrongs the Apoſtle, who never taught nor intended any ſuch doctrine, but ſaid, Overcome evil with good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21. and love bears all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7. Now ſee whoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter this man is, that cannot bear, but would have them ſtoned, and would have the Apoſtle as bad as himſelf, which Apoſtle ſaid, Chriſt was his example, who laid down his life for his enemies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. who ſuffered the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of ſinners, we will render evill to no man, but ſay the contrary, the Lord Jeſus forgive them, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.34. and the Apoſtle ſaid, they wreſtled not againſt fleſh and blood, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 6.12. but them and you that ſtone, do ye not wreſtle againſt fleſh and blood? But if the Apoſtles would have ſtoned, would they not have wreſtled againſt fleſh and Blood? And if the Apoſtles ſhould have ſtoned all that were contrary to their mindes, and bidding the people ſtone them, and told them it was Chriſtian zeal,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171845:7"/>what work would they have made? as the ſaid <hi>Henry Foreſide,</hi> called Miniſter, doth, where would have been long ſuffering, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. and loving enemies? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. and where would he have had any to have converted and who would have been perſecutors? and who would have prayed for perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors? ye may ſee what a pit ye are fallen into, and how ſhould they have convinced gain-ſayers, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9. and loved them whem they had ſtoned them.</p>
               <p>And this is the Presbyterians zeal of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and not Chriſtian zeal, who would ſtone, and ſtir up his congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to do ſo; for Chriſt, who is clothed with zeal, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.17 ſaid, <hi>Love your Enemies,</hi> but ye are cloathed with madneſs and folly: And the Apoſtle that was in his zeal according to knowledge ſaid, Overcome evil with good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21. amd vengeance is the Lords, and he will repay it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19. and love bears all things, but his blind zeal cannot bear any thing, but cryes ſtone them out of the way, and ſo wickedly and deviliſhly calls it Chriſtian zeal, which is falſe that is, the Devils zeal. Now the Apoſtles wreſtled not againſt fleſh and blood, but againſt the powers of darkneſs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12. but the Presbyterians called Miniſters are ſtriking againſt fleſh and blood, whilſt ye would ſtone them, whilſt that time ſpirituall wickedneſſe lies within you. So ye Presbyterian-Prieſts are as a troop of robbers that would murther in the way by conſent, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>James Dorram,</hi> called Miniſter of <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> his Principles.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. THat the believers, even the reall godly, are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin in this life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here is one that is charging the elect, and laying ſin to the elect that God juſtifies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. that in the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there ſhould be ſin. Sin is out of the godly, in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, which turne the grace of God into wantonneſs; and and what good doth his preaching doe them, if they muſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171845:7"/>never be without ſin whilſt they are upon earth, they can be but in their ſin, if they never preach to them: But the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He that believes is borne of God, and he that is borne of God cannot ſin, becauſe his ſeed remaines in him;</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9. But this is of another world to him, who is called <hi>James Dorram</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> Miniſter of darkneſſe, who puts no difference betwen the children of God, and the children of the Devill, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.10. They would have ſin whilſt they are upon the earth, and it is darkneſſe, but the Apoſtles ſaid they were made free from ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22 whilſt they were upon the earth.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>Chriſt being ſinleſſe, ſeperates him from all others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt being ſeparated from ſinners, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26. who are in Chriſt are ſeparated from ſinners and ſin both, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. But this <hi>Ja Dorram</hi> hath made the offering of none effect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. which hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified; And hath made the blood of Jeſus of none effect, which cleanſeth from all ſin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. And he hath made the everlaſting Covenant of none effect which blots out all ſins &amp; treſpaſſes: And he hath made the faith of the Son of God of none effect, which purifies the heart, and gives victory over the world, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.5. Thou doſt herein preach &amp; hold up ſin, and doth not preach it down; and yet thou ſaieſt thou preacheſt not to hold it up, and yet thou preacheſt they muſt have it whilſt they are upon the earth; here is confuſion in thy tongue; <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.20. Thou ſhouldſt have preached it down, and have brought them to a Church where there is neither ſpot nor wrinkle, nor blemiſh, nor any ſuch thing. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. if thou were a true Miniſter, but your Church is full of ſpots, and blemiſhes, and wrinkels, whilſt ye are preaching up zeal to ſtone people, and ſin while they live, as <hi>Henry Foreſide, and James Dorram</hi> doth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. God be thanked, the ſcripture ſpeaks nothing for freedom from ſin and perfection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Thou thankeſt God that thou maiſt live in thy ſin and imperfection, and art glad of thy falſe hope; but thou art a lyar, thou art out of the truth in this, for the Scripture
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171845:8"/>ſaith they were made free from ſin, <hi>Rom:</hi> 6:26: and they preached wiſdom among them that were perfect, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2:6: and he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10:14: So the ſcripture ſpeakes of freedom from ſin and perfection, and be perfect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr: That the condemning power of ſin is taken away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> The believer doth not ſin, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5:1: 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3:9: but he that the believer overcomes commits ſin, 1 <hi>Io:</hi> 3:8: and 1 <hi>Io:</hi> 5:5: and if the believer commits ſin, who overcomes the believer? and ſo he that commits ſin is under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning power of ſin which thou ſaiſt not: which thou and all other ſhall witneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr: The believer is not in ſin as the unbeliever is, he ſins not as the unbeliever doth and in an other place he ſaith, the Law is the ſame to the believer, that it is to the unbeliever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Here any may read thy confuſion, but I ſay unto thee, he that believeth doth not commit ſin, but the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is ſin, <hi>Rom:</hi> 11:20: and Chriſt is the end of the Law to every one that believes for righteouſneſs ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. and yet thou puts both believers and unbelievers under the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Lodowick Simerell,</hi> Prieſt of the new pariſh of <hi>Munckland,</hi> his Principles and Doctrines.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. THat it is blaſphemy to ſay that the light in man, which reproves of ſin, is the light of God, is perfect, is the gift of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Contrary to ſcripture, contrary to Chriſts words, and contrary to the Apoſtles words is thy doctrine and Principles, for every gift of God is perfect, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. For Chriſt is the gift of God, and he hath given him for a Covenant of light to the Jews and Gentiles, which doth enlighten every man that commeth into the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171845:8"/>world, which every one that doth truth comes to it, which every one that doth evil hates the light, and will not come to the light, becauſe the light will reprove him; and ſo, This is the condemnation of the world, that light is come into the world, and men love darkeneſſe rather then light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds be evill. So this light is perfect, which doth reprove every man of ſin, and is from above, and it is the gift of God, and thou art blind and in darkneſs that comprehends it not: And the light which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, Chriſt Jeſus the gift of God, him by whom the world was made: this light was before any naturall light was made, Sun, Moon, or Stars; for all things that was made, was made by the light, which came a light into the world, that all through him might believe, for he that believes not in the light, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already; and he that does believe in the light hath the witneſſe in himſelf, to ſet to his ſeal that God is true, and the ſpirit of truth that doth reprove the world, is perfect, and of God.</p>
               <p>The light which every one that cometh into the world is enlightened withall, is not conſcience, for the light was before any thing was made, or conſcience named: So the light is that which exerciſeth the conſcience towards God, and towards man, where it is loved, and the voice heard; but where it is hated, and the voice not heard, the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſeared, and the light is their condemnation, whoſe conſciences is ſeared, which light was before conſcience was.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt would not have <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> to be to a ſingle perſon, and ſo is the man that would not indure ſound words, that cannot be condemned, <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> was the language between God and his Saints, and one another, and <hi>you</hi> is to many, and <hi>thou</hi> was to one, and this was the language between <hi>Jeptha</hi> and his daughter, and between the Saints and the Kings, this ſhewes thou haſt not learned the Accidence nor Bible, nor art come to the form of ſound words.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171845:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171845:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:171845:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>John Caſtaires,</hi> called Miniſter of <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> his Principles.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. TIs naturall folkes duty to pray to God, and worſhip him, although they ſinfully keep themſelves under a ſinfull neceſſity to ſin againſt God through ignorance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> This hath been your worke to keep people in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, which you may be aſhamed of. A natural man cannot worſhip God, for he cannot receive the things of God; nor a ſinfull man, but worſhip the Devil; for he that commits ſin, ſerves him; and he that ſerves ſin, ſerves the Devill, and worſhips him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8:34: And Chriſt ſaid the Phariſees ſhould receive the greater damnation, for their pretended long prayers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23:14: and ſo he did not juſtifie them in their long prayers, but rebuked them, and ſaid, Wo unto them who draw near with their lips, when their hearts were far off, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29:13: And they that pray and worſhip God, muſt pray in the ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 14:15: and worſhip in the Spirit, which the Devil is out of, <hi>John</hi> 4:21:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr: If the firſt Command be in force, and if it be in force negatively, it is alſo in force, poſitively, thou ſhalt have me for thy God, and oughteſt to worſhip me, and if they pray not as they ſhould, let them anſwer for it, for it is not ſin of it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that the Commandments were given unto, knew God, but the Heathen knows him not: here all may ſee what meaſure thou meaſures withall. And further thou ſayeſt, if they pray as they ſhould not, and yet not ſin, is praying as they ſhould, and as they ſhould not, one? by this to call upon God with their lips, and the heart not right, and the prayers and ſacrifice of the wicked is juſtified, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. and if any pray as they ſhould not, are they not condemned for it? and if in praying as they ſhould not, be not ſin, then they doe as they ſhould.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. If folks ſhould not pray becauſe they are uncapable, then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171845:10"/>a believer not finding himſelf in a good frame, may let his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> A Believer is ababe of God, and his cry is right, his prayer is right, and his groan is right, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. And every man that cometh into the world, being enlightned, and coming into the light which hath enlightned him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. in that he is to watch and pray, which leads him beyond naturals, which will be accepted in the degree, but he that hates the light, his prayer is not accepted, but is in the hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. The Apoſtles bad</hi> Simon Magus, <hi>an old witchcarle, pray, and now is there any reaſon to ſay we are bidding folk ſin when we bid them pray, although they be groſly ignorant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Apoſtle bad him Repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.22. and he was ſenſible he had ſinned: and that which makes a man ſenſible of ſinne, brings him to pray aright, and turnes him from witchcraft, and ſo thou doſt put no difference between the precious and the vile, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. the accepted and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accepted.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Hen. Foreſide,</hi> who would have had his people to ſtone the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and calls it Chriſtian zeal, he would have his wall up that he might live in ſafety, who murthers, and would be preſerved in the murtherous eſtate, and would have the powers of the earth to be his Executioners and pack-horſes, but the Lord is opening of their eyes, that they will not execute their malice, though he is ſtirring up the people to do ſo; ſo all may ſee this is not the work of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but the work of the Murtherer, and one that makes himſelf drunk with the blood of the Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.6. till he reel again in his madneſſe. And Chriſt called them that took up ſtones to ſtone him, of their Father the Devil, for doing his luſt, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. And thou who would have the people to ſtone, and calls it Chriſtian zeal, thou haſt manifeſted thy Father, and to be of the Devil, who was a Murtherer from the beginning, but you are the Serpents and vipers that would kill to fill the meaſure of your Fathers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.32. and perſecute from City to City, and hale out of the Synagouges, <hi>John</hi> 16.2. that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171845:11"/>all the unrighteous blood, ſhed from righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> might come upon you, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35. and you are they that kill the bodies of the Saints, and are ſheders of the righteous blood, (Mark, the righteous blood) that the righteous blood might be upon you. And <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe <hi>Abels</hi> ſacrifice was accepted, and his not, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. So it is about the Sacrifice, and worſhip, ye would murther and ſlay: So ye are in <hi>Cains</hi> way, a company of vagabonds, whoſe Sacrifice God hath no reſpect unto; if we were enemies, you would not teach the people to ſtone us if ye were Miniſters of Chriſt, but love us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. And do good to us. If the Apoſtles ſhould have taught the people to ſtone all that were contrary to their minde, and Chriſt ſhould have taught his Diſciples to ſtone all that were contrary to their minde, and tell them that were Chriſtian zeale, but ye may ſee Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught another doctrine, Love your Enemies, and thou teacheſt to ſtone them, contrary to Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, we do conclude it to be the Doctrine of the Devil, and not the Doctrine of Chriſt, who are in ſcorne called <hi>Quakers.</hi> For the true Chriſtian zeal never taught to ſtone, but were ſtoned.</p>
               <p>The Prieſts called <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſummoned ſome people called <hi>Quakers</hi> to come before them, and they came into the Steeple houſe where they met, and <hi>James Naſmith,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Hanbleton</hi> bad them remove, or elſe he would make them remove by Club Law, and they asked the presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Prieſts for their accuſers, and <hi>Francis Ard</hi> one of the Prieſts ſaid, they were both accuſers and Judges; now whether this be equity, that the ſame ſhould be both accuſers, and Judges that ſummons; and when they have ſummoned, accuſed, and judged, ſaith they will make them remove by club Law: whether theſe be not bruits, and beaſts, and not Juſtices, and are not fit to Judge, nor to have the name of Miniſters, and Judges that will remove people by club Law; and the ſaid <hi>Quakers</hi> could not own them as Judges, nor doth look on them as men of equity, but would have had them to have given them a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171845:11"/>meeting in any place, whereby the truth might be cleared, which they had ſcandalized, and come to light, which they refuſed, and that lawful witneſſes might hear, but they did refuſe, and cauſed them to be put in priſon by the hand of a Baliffe, by name <hi>Naſmith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is the authority of the Presbyterian Prieſts, who hath ſummoned with club Law, but it is denyed by the Apoſtles Doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. they muſt not be ſtrikers, nor falſe accuſers. Theſe are the Presbyterian Prieſts of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> weapons, club Law, which is contrary to the Miniſters of Chriſt, they ſaid, <hi>We wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood, and they muſt not be ſtrikers,</hi> Eph. 6.12. and after they had done violently, they thruſt them into priſon; after their wills were ſatisfied with violence, they thruſt them out again, there ye may feel the Spirit of wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>And theſe Presbyterian Prieſts, (are people) petitions the Magiſtrates, with a pretence, they might not be guilty of others blood, which pretence is in their Petitions, to take away their fear, that their wicked peace might not be diſturbed, not regarding their blood: witneſſe <hi>James Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith</hi> Prieſt, who would make them remove by club Law. So their Petition is but flattery and deceit, in pretence of not being guilty of their blood, in whoſe heart it is to ſhed blood, as witneſs <hi>Henry Foreſide</hi> Prieſt, who ſtirred up the people in zeal to ſtone them.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Presbyterian Prieſts that ſet up club Law and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who would not have any to receive them into their houſes. So this is abominable Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, contrary to the Apoſtle, whoſe Doctrine you have troden under your feet, who ſaid, <hi>Be not forgetful to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Strangers, for thereby ſome have entertained Angels un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares,</hi> Heb. 13.2.</p>
               <p>And they ſay again, They have no certain dwelling places. Here theſe Presbyterians with their club Law and Excommunications, which ſay the Quakers have no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain dwelling places, they may inform againſt the Apoſtles, which had no ceartain dwelling places, and againſt Chriſt, who had not whereon to lay his head, <hi>Luk</hi> 9.58. and againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171845:12"/>
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> who had not a foot of ground, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. but <hi>Cain</hi> built a City, the vagabond, of whoſe ſtock and off-ſpring you are, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.17. and ſaid <hi>David,</hi> Let their Children be vagabonds, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.10. and ſo this is fulfilled upon you.</p>
               <p>And you Presbyterian Prieſts with your club Law, who would club thoſe people ſcornfully called Quakers, away; you would have an Order from the Juſtices, that none ſhould receive the Quakers into there houſes, and ſtop them of their liberty; and this is contrary to the Law of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And this is damnable doctrine, wherewith ye poiſon the people, and ſtirs them up with madneſs and folly. And in ſtead of teaching of them peace, you teach them ſtrife, and in ſtead of loving one another, you teach them to fight one with another.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Henry Foreſide</hi> Prieſt cryes ſtone them. And <hi>James Naſmith</hi> Prieſt cryes for club Law. And <hi>William Hambleton</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Glaſford</hi> ſaid to <hi>Andrew Brown,</hi> if the Lawes were right, they would chop off all the Quakers heads: by <hi>William Hambletons</hi> words the Law is wrong, becauſe it doth not fulfill his purpoſe and envy.</p>
               <p>Here all may ſee that you are doing the Devils work, hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after blood, whoſe envy, madneſs and folly appeares to all men; what ye cannot do your ſelves, ye exhort the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to do; and what ye and the people cannot do, ye Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition the Magiſtrates to do, that all the righteous blood may come upon you, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35.</p>
               <p>Alas for you, ye poor filly Prieſts, and mad Presbiterians: Is this your work to ſet them to ſtone, and cry up club Law, and Law to chop off their heads? is this the way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them? is not this the Popiſh way of converting them? ye ſhould go to convert them, inſtruct them, convince them, love them, heap coals of fire upon them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 20. Overcome evil with good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21. Pray for them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. No cry you, chop off their heads, begging by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions that none may receive them into their houſes, ſtone them, fall upon them by club law, that your folly and madneſs may be made manifeſt; and yet impriſon them, and ſuch as receive them into their houſes: As for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171845:12"/>inſtance, ye cauſed <hi>John Hart</hi> of the heads of <hi>Glaſford,</hi> and <hi>Jennet Hambleton</hi> widdow of <hi>Weſtmanes,</hi> to be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for entertaining them into their houſes. Here ye have proved your ſelves to be the Wolves the ſheep are ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16. that are ravening to devoure them; which is one of the markes that ye are the falſe Prophets Chriſt ſaid ſhould come <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.5. And another haling out of the Synagogues, and Excommunicating, and ye never ſhew for what; which practice ye are in, which is a work of darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>and upon this bargaine that the Magiſtrates would grant them an order, that none ſhould receive them into their houſes, and that they might not have their liberty, and their ſervants would be much refreſhed, who cry ſtone them, let us have a Law againſt them, and if the Laws were right, they would chop off their heads, and make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move by club Law; but how was theſe Prieſts the Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſervants at <hi>Dunbar</hi> Fight, when they excommunicated and curſed their now being army and Magiſtracy? but now they would be their ſervants, if they would execute their wills upon the innocent: Surely theſe things cannot but ſtinck to all Magiſtrates that feare God.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the ſervants and ſervers of the times, that the Prophets calls inchanters, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.16. and for their own falſe ends; ye can never read that the Apoſtles nor Chriſt did ever teach any ſuch doctrine that the people ſhould be ſtoned, or have their heads choped off, or driven away by clup Law, which ſhewes you are Apoſtatates, from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, and of the Jewiſh nature.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> in the ſecond moneth, did ordain concerning theſe perſons in <hi>Clidſdale,</hi> formerly Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, who are called Quakers, that no other people in other pariſhes ſhould bargain with them, or ſuffer them to come within their houſes, or have entertainment for mony: Upon which the people perſecuted, and ſtoned them, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them out of their houſes in ſeveral places, <hi>viz.</hi> Three of them people called Quakers, were in the night time between the 10. and 11. hours, drawn by force out of an Inne, in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171845:13"/>Town of <hi>New mills</hi> in <hi>Aire-ſhire,</hi> and ſtoned out of the town into the Fields to ſhift for their lodging. And others, three ſeverall times were beaten, ſtoned, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully intreated, and perſecuted in <hi>Stravan.</hi> And others at <hi>Lithmahaga.</hi> And others ſhamefully abuſed in the Town of <hi>Kirkantillough.</hi> And others ſtoned at <hi>Kilbride.</hi> And others pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully ſtoned, beaten and abuſed; and ſome blood ſhed at <hi>Glaſford:</hi> And at many other places much harme hath been done. Theſe be the Prieſts fruits, the bloody Presbytery, who would have them ſtoned, and their heads chopped off; ſome of the Magiſtrates did ſtop the people for abuſing of them, ſo that the Prieſts malice was not altogether ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andrew Brown,</hi> and <hi>John Lacock</hi> of <hi>Glaſford,</hi> were caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to priſon, for asking him a queſtion when he was Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and admoniſhed them when they were far abſent, and if they come before them, they will caſt them into priſon; this makes them peepers and mutterers, to admoniſh them when they are not preſent, and is this like to change them, or do they intend to change them, who admoniſh them when they are out of hearing, and did Excommunicate them when they were in priſon? what an unhumanly part is this wicked, develiſh, envious, and unchriſtian Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>And <hi>John Hart</hi> went to a ſteeple houſe to here the Prieſts admoniſhment, for the Prieſt ſaid he would admoniſh him, and he went to hear him, and when he had admoniſhed him, he ſpake to him, and bid him prove himſelf in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of Chriſt, and they who he admoniſhed out of it, and then give them a bill of divorſment: but the Prieſts went to the Court, and got a warrant from the Juſtice, and ſo caſt him into priſon, and when he was in priſon, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him, and ſaid he diſturbed him; And here his deviliſh wicked art &amp; doctrine appears, which ſhews him of <hi>Cains</hi> flock, where is nothing but perſecution, murther, and envious-ſlayers, vagabonds, &amp; curſed ſpeakers that went on in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> or <hi>Core;</hi> that makes merchandize of the people through their covetouſneſſe, and feigned words to the people; And gives forth their Curſes in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and all the people are to ſay Amen to them as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:171845:13"/>
               <head>The Prieſts firſt <hi>Curſe</hi> that all the people were to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to.</head>
               <head type="sub">Curſed be all they that ſay Grace is free, and let all the people ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> ANd ſo they curſe the Apoſtles, and the Apoſtles doctrine, and all that witneſſe to it, who ſaid, The free grace of God <hi>which bringeth ſalvation hath appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all men,</hi> Tit. 2.11. and was the Saints Teacher; theſe things the Apoſtles commanded to teach with all authority, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15. but the ungodly men turn this grace of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wantonneſs, of old ordained for condemnation.</p>
               <p>Ye are the raging waves of the Sea, ſending and foming out your own ſhame, whoſe fruits wither, neglecting the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſalvation, read <hi>Jude.</hi> Ye are like to <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> clouds without water, who run greedily after the wages of <hi>Balaam,</hi> going on the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and ſhall periſh in the gain-ſaying of <hi>Core,</hi> and walking deſpitefully againſt the ſpirit of grace; and they that turn the grace of God into wantonneſs, denies the Lord that bought them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Jude</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Ye are the trees without fruit, wells without water, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about with tempeſts, curſed ſpeakers; teaching the people to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to your curſing the Apoſtles doctrine, and ſo willingly ignorant, that your damnation may be juſt, that your madneſs and folly might appear to all, and ſo ſenſual, having not the ſpirit, waves of the Sea, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſtars, received for darkneſs of blackneſs, read <hi>Jude. The grace of God which bringeth ſalvation hath appeared to all men,</hi> Tit. 2.11. So that which brings ſalvation, and hath appeared to all men, ye curſe that which is the grace of God, which ye with your damnable doctrine, and doctrine of Devils, curſe them that witneſs it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. upon whoſe conſciences the hot Iron hath come,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171845:14"/>hardned them that went to the doctrine of Devils, went to them that did not hold forth the Saviour of all men, but eſpeciall them that beleeve, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Theſe things command and teach, let no man deſpiſe thy youth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now they that went to the doctrine of Devils, from the Saviour of all men, but eſpecially them that believe, and from the grace of God which hath appeared to all men, which brings ſalvation; are they which have turned the grace of God into wantonneſs, ordained of old for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which is the light, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. Such be in <hi>Cains</hi> way from the command of God, <hi>Cores</hi> way from the truth, and <hi>Balaams</hi> way from the ſpirit, thoſe be the clouds and tempeſts upon whoſe heads comes the Woe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Prieſts ſecond <hi>Curſe,</hi> which all the People were to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to.</head>
               <head type="sub">Curſed be all they that ſay, the Scriptures is not the Word of God; and let all the people ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> HEre they have curſed <hi>Luke,</hi> who calls the Scripture a Declaration of the Word, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1. and <hi>Acts</hi> 1.1. where it is called a Treatiſe; and they have curſed their own company who ſay the Scriptures ſignifies writings; and they have curſed <hi>John,</hi> who did not ſay the Scripture was the Word, who ſaid, <hi>In the beginning was the Word,</hi> Joh. 1.1. and the Scripture is words, as <hi>Revel.</hi> the laſt, He that addeth to the words; and Chriſt his name is called, <hi>The Word of God, Rev.</hi> 19.13. And the Scriptures are words, not a word, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. and which words Chriſt came to fulfill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:171845:14"/>
               <head>The Prieſts third <hi>Curſe,</hi> to which all the people were to ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Curſed be all they that ſay Faith is without ſin, and let all the people ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> FAith is the gift of God, and the gift of God is without ſin, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. Faith is that which gives the victory, <hi>John</hi> 3.4. And that which gives victory is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin. And here they have curſed the Apoſtles and their Doctrine, who ſaith, Faith is without ſin, and Faith is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. and that which is Precious is without ſin. Faith is the gift of God, and the gift of God is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and that which is perfect is without ſin, and gives victory over ſin: Without Faith a man cannot pleaſe God, and that which men pleaſe God in, is without ſin, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6. And ſo ye have curſed the Apoſtle and his Doctrine, the juſt and that which is pure, that by which they were healed, through Faith they were juſtified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. and what is not of Faith is ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. So what is of Faith is not ſin, and what is righteous is not ſin, and the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſpeaks of the righteouſneſs of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. Faith is not of ſin, but what is not of Faith is ſin, Faith gives victory over ſin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.4. in which Faith man is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and hath peace with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. and it is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery held in a pure conſcience, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:171845:15"/>
               <head>The Prieſts fourth <hi>Curſe,</hi> to which all the people were to ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Curſed are all they that ſay every man hath a light ſufficient to lead him to Chriſt, and that within him, and let all the people ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> HEre they have curſed the Apoſtles Doctrine, who ſaid God would dwell in them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. and Chriſt in you the hope of glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. and God is light, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5. And they have curſed the Prophets, who ſaid, I give him for a Covenant, a Leader of the people: I will dwell in them, and walk in them, ſaith God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.16. And he ſaith, I will ſend you the Spirit of truth, and it ſhall lead you into all truth, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. <hi>John</hi> 16: 13. And I will be their God, to rule them, and they ſhall be my people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. Thy curſes are but winde, for we are redeemed from the curſe; and the Apoſtles ſaid, the light that ſhined in their hearts was to give them the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. and they that are led by the Spirit of God are the Sons of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. and the light to guide our feet in the way of peace, and he that hath the Son hath the Father alſo; and if any bring another Doctrine, receive them not into your houſes, neither bid them God ſpeed, 2 <hi>John</hi> 9, 10. You have here ſhewed your ſelves in the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate, out of the Apoſtles rule, the ſame ſpirit of truth that led the Diſciples into all truth, that ſhall reprove the world of ſin, <hi>John</hi> 16.8, 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:171845:15"/>
               <head>The Prieſts fifth <hi>Curſe,</hi> to which all the people were to ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Curſed be all they that deny the Sabbath-day, and let all the people ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> HEre thou haſt curſed thy ſelf, and all the Apoſtles, and all the Saints, and their own generation; haſt not thou and thy own generation denied the Sabbath day, the <hi>Jews</hi> met on, which is the Sabbath day according to the Scripture? do not ye meet together upon the firſt day? and was not Chriſt crucified on the ſixth day? and did not he ariſe on the firſt day? and did not the Saints meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the firſt day? and not keep the <hi>Jews</hi> Sabbath-day? do not you work upon it your ſelves, and keep Markets and Fairs on it? but as it is ſaid before, we are Redeemed from the curſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the particular Sentences whereupon <hi>Matthew Mackell,</hi> and the reſt of the Prieſts preſent with him, did excommunicate thoſe people called <hi>Quakers</hi> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of many witneſſes, and he required his Hearers to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to every particular ſentence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>John Humes,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Liſmahagow,</hi> his Principles.</head>
               <p>Pr. <hi>THey who have not the Scriptures, knowes not the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of God by the light of nature, but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declare the great myſtery of the three perſons in Trinity, which they who want the Scriptures knowes not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thy Principle is a lie, and they that had not the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures knew God and Chriſt, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Enoch,</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171845:16"/>the Scripture doth not declare of the three perſons, nor of the Trinity, and the natural man receives not the things of the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>That the Scriptures reveal the great myſtery of Election, the great works of the Creation, and the work of Redemption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There thou haſt ſet up the Scripture inſtead of God, and before God and the Son, for it is God that doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal to babes and ſucklings, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. and God did reveal by his Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. and God ſhall reveal, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. and the things of God are hid from the wiſe and prudent, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. that have the Scriptures; the <hi>Jewes</hi> had the Scriptures: and God reveals his ſecrets to the Prophets his Servants, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.7. no man knowes the Father ſaving to whom the Son ſhall reveal him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.17. now the Son reveals, and the Father reveals, and the things of God are revealed by his Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. the <hi>Jewes</hi> had the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and knew not the Son, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. nor the Father, as in <hi>John,</hi> nor the things of God by a natural light, as they call it; the <hi>Jewes</hi> had the Scriptures, and did not know the Election, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24. becauſe they were from the Spirit. So it is God that reveals the Son, and Redemption, and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and not the Scripture, the Scripture was given forth from them that had the Revelation from God.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>That wee and the Papiſts and Jeſuites, and Prieſts, do agree all together, that the Scripture is the word of God that liveth and endureth for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I do believe that you and the Papiſts and Jeſuits, agree all in one; but ye did not agree with the Apoſtles and Miniſters of the word, for the Miniſters of the word calls the Scripture <hi>a Declaration,</hi> as ye may read <hi>Luke</hi> 1. and ye do not agree with them that ſet forth the <hi>Acts,</hi> that called it a Treatiſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. likewiſe ye do not agree with ſome of your own, who ſay the Scriptures ſignifies writings, and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings will not endure for ever, ſo ye are <hi>Babylon,</hi> and do not agree with Chriſt, and ye do not agree with <hi>John, Bev.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. who ſaith the words; nor with <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor God, who ſpake all theſe words, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. In the beginning was the word, and the word is God, and the word liveth and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171845:16"/>for ever; but the Scripture is words, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot be broken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>James Neſmith</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Hambleton,</hi> his Principles.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. THat the ſoul of man is a reaſonable ſinfull ſubſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How can that which is ſinful be reaſonable? and if that which is unſinful be reaſonable, and ſinful be reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable both, then they are one in unity: The Lord will take the ſoul for an offering for ſin; doth the Lord take that which is ſinful for an offerring? <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53. ſee how thou and the Prophet agrees here; But what is that ſoul that the wicked is not able to kill? is it not that which God hath in his hand? and this is a lye, to ſay that which is reaſonable is ſinful, of one that puts light for darkneſſe. God breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into man the breath of life, and he became a living ſoul, who hath all ſouls in his hand, and the ſoul is immortal, and Chriſt the Biſhop of it is immortal, and God hath it in his hand which goeth againſt him that doeth evil, whoſe hand is immortal, but man tranſgreſſing againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, the ſoul lies in death; ſo Chriſt is the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the ſouls, ſo they that came to know Chriſt, their ſouls rejoyce in God their Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. That the evil Spirits are both ſinfull and reaſonable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a lie for reaſonable is not ſinful, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable is ſinful, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. they have not the faith: and if the evil Spirit be reaſonable, and the good reaſonable, they are both one, who then is unreaſonable? If the evil Spirit be reaſonable, thou pots no difference between the precious and the vile; thou haſt the Mark of a blind guide, and a falſe Prophet in thy ſo ehead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. That one of them</hi> Quakers <hi>is worſe then the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This is a lie with his ſtrange wonder, for there is nothing worſe then the Devil, whoſe children you are for when he ſpeaks a lie he ſpeakes of himſelf, and he is the Father of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:171845:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Henry Foreſide</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Lingiah</hi> in <hi>Dunbarton ſhire,</hi> His Doctrine and PRINCIPLES.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr. THat God commands all every where to repent, to the end that they ſhould not have it to ſay but they were warned, but not that he would give them grace to repent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here thou makes God that he does not intend that he ſpeaks, and ſo thou would make him unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though the Lord commands all men every where to repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. who hath made all Nations of men of one blood to dwell upon the Earth, and all being concluded under ſin and unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9. For both <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> all were under ſin, and none of them did good, no not one. And Gods intent is, that when he calls men to repentance, they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, when he calls them, and many did repent; and you are not fit men to be Miniſters of Chriſt or God.</p>
               <p>Now if God command all men every where to Repent, and, as thou ſayſt, does not intend they ſhould Repent, thou and you go about to make God unjuſt. Firſt the Lord he deſireth not the death of a ſinner, but that he ſhould turn from his wickedneſſe and live, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.11. Now in the turning from his wickedneſſe he lives, but in going on in his wickedneſſe he dies; ſo Repentance was Preached from dead works, to ſerve the living God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. &amp; Chriſt came to call finners to Repentance, not the Righteous; for the whole needs not the Phyſitian, but to the ſick, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.12, 13.</p>
               <p>And as for ſaying, God did not intend to give them grace, though he calls them to repentance: That is a lie, &amp; unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous doctrine, for the grace of God hath appeared to all men, which brings Salvation, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11. and ſo as he calls them to repentance, he gives them grace, that grace which brings ſalvation, which men are juſtified by; ſo it is ſaving grace that brings ſalvation, and teacheth to deny ungodlineſſe.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:171845:17"/>
               <p>Now they that live ungodly, turnes the grace of God into wantonneſſe, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. and theſe are the wells without water, in <hi>Cains</hi> way, <hi>Balaams</hi> way, and <hi>Cores</hi> way, <hi>Jude</hi> 11. ſpeaks the high words in hypocriſie; and theſe are they that ſeparate themſelves from the Apoſtles, ſenſual, having not the Spirit, <hi>Jude</hi> 19. and are of old ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to condemnation, who ſeparated from the light, which turnes the grace of God into wantonneſſe; ſo theſe are they that neglect the common ſalvation, it was the charge of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> before his deceaſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. Then told him perillous times ſhould come, and Doctrines of Devils, and men ſpeaking lies in hypocriſie; he ſaid unto them, that they ſhould truſt in the living God, who is the Saviour of all men, and eſpecially of them that believe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. But the Devils Doctrine leads them from their Saviour, and from the grace, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. And they that are not in the Doctrine, are from the light, which Chriſt hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned them withall, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. And have turned the grace of God into wantonneſſe, and pernitious wayes, and drawes others from it, and we do conclude that to be the Doctrine of Devils, which ſayes God calls all men to repent, and intends not to give them grace, nor would not have them to repent: as thou <hi>Henry Foreſide</hi> doth ſay, for it was the charge of the Apoſtle to <hi>Titus</hi> to ſpeak ſound words, and ſound Doctrine, and could not be condemned, <hi>Titus</hi> 2. and told him that the grace of God which brings ſalvation had appeared to all men, which taught them to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſt, and to live godly, ſoberly and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in this preſent evill world, theſe things ſpeak and exhort with all authority, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. But as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ungodly men that turn the grace of God into wantonneſſe, are of old ordained to this condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and this the is condemnation of the world, that light is come into the World, and men love darkneſſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then light, becauſe their deeds are evill, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. he that loves the light, the light is his Saviour, but he that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171845:18"/>hates the light, it is his condemnation.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>That the two parts of the Church muſt be prophane and godleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Church is the Pillar and ground of truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. The Church of the living God; for the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are out of its grounds, and that which is ungodly; the pillar and ground of truth, there is no ungodly in it, and the Church is without wrinkle or ſpot, holy, without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. and the Church is in God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. That which is in God is in the light, and out of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>That God before the world was, had ordained one little part of the people for eternal life; that ſin, or do all the evil they could, they could not looſe that which was ordained for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here thou goeſt about to make Chriſt a lyar, for he that commits ſin is the ſervant of ſin, 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 3.8. ſaith, He that commits ſin is of the Devil, ſaith the Apoſtle, and thou wouldſt make God partial, and haſt taught a Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Scriptures, For God is no reſpecter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.11. Who will give to every one a reward ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their works, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.12. And he that works ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity muſt depart curſed from Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25: 41. And he that ſinneth after he hath received the truth, there remains no more ſacrifice for ſin, but a fearful look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for of judgement, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.27. And the elect doth not commit ſin, and who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. and the Elect is Chriſt, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.1. who was elected before the world was, he that is born of God doth not commit ſin, neither can he, becauſe his ſeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. And he that commits ſin is of the Devil, and never knew God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6: And here is the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God manieſt, and the children of the Devil, 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 3:10: and God hears not ſinners, and them that regard iniquity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.31. <hi>Prov:</hi> 15: 8:</p>
               <p>Pr: <hi>That the great part of the world was ordained for Hell, that repent or do all that they are commanded to doe, they would not obtain ſalvation, becauſe God had ordained them to Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:171845:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Then he was asked wherefore he preached? His an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was to ſave the elect: he was anſwered again, if it was ſo, there was no need of that, ſeeing they could not be loſt; Then he was asked before he preached to them that were ordained to Hell: he anſwered to make their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hotter; it was anſwered them again, that they had ſmall friends of them, and they could not make it hotter, ſeeing they were ordained before; the Prieſt aforeſaid was asked, who had the blame that men went to Hell.</p>
               <p>His anſwer was, <hi>Seeing ye deſire to know, I ſhall tell you, there is one part of the blame in man, and another part of the blame in the Almighty, that men went to Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In this here is confuſion, thou ſayeſt, <hi>God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained them,</hi> thou ſayeſt God has done it, (then mark) then thou ſayeſt, <hi>there is part in man,</hi> and thou ſayeſt before it was in God; now if it be in God, as thou ſayeſt, that he hath ordained them to hell, repent or do all that they are commanded to do, thy preaching is needleſs; and thou cannot add to Hell hotter or colder: Therefore thy preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is done and ceaſed: And thou ſaiſt part of the blame that men go to hell is in God; here thou wouldeſt make God unrighteous, who deſires not the death of a ſinner, God is not to be blamed in any thing he doth, but praiſed, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in all his judgements; and God is not to be blamed, for God is truth, ſo let God be true, and every man a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4. thou wicked one, mans deſtruction is of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9: and God wills not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he would repent, ſo no fault in God, who ſaith, let the unrighteous man forſake his unrighteouſneſs, and he ſhall live; ſo let the righteous man forſake his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and he dies, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.22. So my ways are equall, the Lord hath no pleaſure at all that the wicked ſhould die, but that he ſhould return and live, ſo mans deſtruction is of himſelf: And whereas thou ſayeſt, <hi>God hath ordained a great part to Hell,</hi> what makeſt thou of Chriſt who came to be a Saviour of the world? <hi>John</hi> 4.42. he doth not ſay the Elect onely, but to ſave the world, and not to condemn it, and God ſo loved the world (mark the words) <hi>John</hi> 3.19.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171845:19"/>he doth not ſay, ſo hated it, that he gave his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son into the world, that whoſoever believed in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life; and he came not to condemn the world, but that the world through him might have life, but they that hate the light, and do not beleeve in it, are with the light condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but thou ſayeſt otherwiſe, that he condemns a great part of the world, and he doth not ſay he loves the Elect onely, but God ſo loved the world, and God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. he does not ſay the Elect onely; and he through death hath deſtroyed the power of death, the Devil, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. and thou art to be reproved for thy judgment, for thy unbelief, for thy righteouſneſs, for thy ſin, becauſe of thy unbelief, for thy judgment, becauſe the Prince of this world is judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. and ſo Chriſt doth not ſay I am the light of the Saints, of the elect onely, but I am the light of the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.12. and ſaith, that light is come into the world, and this is the condemnation of the world, that light is come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to the world, and men love darkneſs rather then it, becauſe their deeds are evil, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.19. So its unbelief that ſhuts out, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. So the gates ſtand open night and day, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that doth evill, hates the light and will not come to it, becauſe it will reprove him, and he will not come in to the gate, for he that comes to the gate comes to the light, and he that comes to the light, comes out of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and comes to be a child of the light, he that hates the light will not come into the kingdome of God: And for thy ſaying, God hath ordained a great part of the world to Hell, let them repent, and do all that ever he hath commanded them; he that doth the things that Chriſt commands, enters the Kingdome; he that repents his mind is changed, and whoſoever beleeveth ſhal not periſh, and this command is general, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28. through the whole world, therefore thou with the Devils doctrine, ſhuts up the kingdome of Heaven againſt others, and wilt not go in thy ſelf, who ſaies let men repent, and do all that ever they can, they muſt go to hell, when God
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171845:19"/>wills not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould turn from his wickedneſs and live, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. but he is merciful, and judges not as thou doſt, whoſe eyes are blinded, and hands full of blood; ſo I ſay, whoſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and doth the things they are commanded, they ſhall be ſaved, and that which thou ſayeſt to the contrary, we conclude to be the Devils doctrine, and whoſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the thing that is commanded, that will be their condemnation, but hates the light which was before the world was, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, that all through him might beleeve, for he that beleeves in the light ſhall not abide in darkneſs, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. ſhall not come into condemnation, ſhall come to be a child of light, <hi>John</hi> 12.36. and they ſhall have the light of life, and ſo the light is ſufficient to ſave them, and condemn them that beleeve not, <hi>John</hi> 3.18.14. <hi>James</hi> 4.12. and every one that cometh into the light, that they are inlightned withal, ſuch come into the election, and into the Covenant of God, and evill conſciences thou mayeſt frighten, them that hates the light, which is their condemnation; but the elect thou canſt neither ſave nor deceive, thanks be to God Chriſt reigns, who will give to every man according to his works, who doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every man that cometh into the world, not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is condemned, and ſhut out, and ſuch turn the grace of God into wantonneſs, and are ordained of old, that hate the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, and ſuch be in <hi>Cain</hi> &amp; <hi>Balaams</hi> way, perſecutors and murtherers, and turns the grace of God into wantonneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> From the words of <hi>Jude</hi> 4. they were of old or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; from theſe words he ſaid, That God had prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated one to life, without any cauſe in the creature leſſe or more, and the other wicked man to Hell without any cauſe in the creature leſſe or more; and both wicked men: And before thou ſaid part of the cauſe that God caſt into hell was in the man, and part in God; In this ſeventh principle and doctrine, thou ſaieſt there is no cauſe in the creature, that God caſt into hell and condemns him, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171845:20"/>in the other thou ſaid, there were part blame in man, and part in God; and here is the Devils Doctrine, a lie found in thy mouth, and thou haſt wreſted, perverted, and wronged that Scripture in <hi>Jude</hi> who ſaith, their is no part in man cauſeth condemnation; that all may ſee you are ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, he ſaith, they were ungodly, they turned the grace of God into laciviouſneſs that brings ſalvation, that denyed the Lord that bought them, <hi>Jude</hi> 11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. They were covetous, made merchandize of the people, through fained words, ſo no covetous nor Idolater ſhall enter into the Kingdome of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. and all they deny the Lord that bought them, but who owns the light that comes from him, which doth enlighten every man that comes into the world, and none ſees him, but with the light that comes from him, and they goe in <hi>Cores</hi> way, and gain-ſayeth the truth, who goe from the light that Chriſt hath enlightned them in the particular, and he that gain-ſayeth the truth, there is a fault in him, and they goe in <hi>Cains</hi> way that are from the command of God, who ſaid if thou doſt well, ſhalt thou not be accepted? and if he did not well, fin lay at the door; now theſe were of old ordained unto condemnation, which turned the grace of God into wantonneſſe, were in <hi>Cains</hi> way, <hi>Cores</hi> way, and brake the commands as <hi>Cain</hi> did, in <hi>Balaams</hi> way, erred from the ſpirit, and admired mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons becauſe of advantage, which <hi>Balaam</hi> did, and loved the wages of unrighteouſnes, and ſo theſe did not do the things they were commanded; <hi>Cain</hi> he did not doe the thing that he was commanded, nor <hi>Core</hi> that offered ſtrange fire, and his company, <hi>Num.</hi> 16. So theſe of old were ordained for this condemnation, which condemnation is the light, <hi>Io.</hi> 3. light foreſees them, and ſees over them, and condemns them, when they ariſe and goes out from the ſpirit of God in them; and here all may ſee, here was fault worthy of condemnation, and thoſe were they that ſenſually ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves from the Apoſtles, and had not the ſpirit, <hi>Jude</hi> 19 in their dayes: which were covetous, which went for the gift and reward, which were like raging waves of the Sea, which were ſpots in feaſts of charity, feaſting,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171845:20"/>feeding without fear, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. Which admired mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons becauſe of advantage, and ſpoke the high words in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, Wells without water, Trees without fruit, raging waves of the Sea, foming out their own ſhame, clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water carryed about with tempeſts, ſpots in the feaſts of charity, like unto <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah</hi> in filthineſs, which goe from the light that does convince them: ſo there is the ſelf ſeparation, and their is the condemnation that comes over them, the light; and theſe are they that ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Apoſtles; which ſaid love your enemies, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. Which are men gone into the world, which be in <hi>Cains</hi> way in envy, in <hi>Cores</hi> way gain-ſaying the light, they are like raging waves of the Sea, foming out their ſhame in their pulpits, ſo you are the men that ſeparates from the Apoſtles, that be in <hi>Cains</hi> way, who be out of the life, and ſacrifice the Saints were in, that would murther, and <hi>Cores</hi> way that gain-ſayeth the light that doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, ſo againſt the common ſalvation, and ye be like <hi>Cain</hi> foming and raging in your Pulpits, and would murther all that are contrary to you, whoſe Sacrifice God acceptes, &amp; yours he does not, &amp; God would have accepted of <hi>Cain,</hi> if he had done well, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. So God is merciful, &amp; a juſt God, but <hi>Cain</hi> he did not well; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wo went out from God againſt him, and ſo there was fault in him &amp; not in God, which was the cauſe of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: ſo you that be in <hi>Balaams</hi> way; for the wages of unrighteouſneſs, admiring mens perſons becauſe of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, Ye are out of the faith that is held without reſpect of perſons, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. and ſo ſeparated from the Apoſtles, to whom Chriſt ſaid, Freely ye have received, freely give, and you will not give freely, who are rageing and foming, without you have augmentations, ſtipends, gleabe Lands, or Tythes, great ſums of money, gifts of rewards from great houſes, ſo you deny the light that enlighteneth every man that cometh into the would, ſo gain-ſayes the common ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Jude</hi> 1. You gain-ſay the truth, that doth enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en every man that cometh into the world, ſo in <hi>Cores</hi> way you are, and would have the perſons of the Saints mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171845:21"/>ſo in <hi>Cains</hi> way, as ye confeſs that ye have not the ſpirit that gave forth the Scriptures, ſo in the ſelf ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ye deny the light that enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world, which is the Lord, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. And ſo denies the Lord that bought you, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. And ſo are for condemnation, who are of that flock that ſeparate themſelves from the Apoſtles, ſenſually, having not the ſpirit, who are in <hi>Cains</hi> way, that would kill and murther, and out of the Apoſtles way, who ſaid love your enemies; who are in <hi>Balaams</hi> way, for gifts and rewards, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mens perſons becauſe of advantage, to them ſpeaking high words in hypocriſy, and out of the Apoſtles way to whom Chriſt ſaid, Freely ye have received, freely give, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.6. And out of the Prophets way, who ſaid, come without a price, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. And ye will have the price, or elſe you will not come, let all that can read <hi>Iude</hi> over, and ſee if their was not cauſe in man of his condemnation, and not in God; and ſo have not you proved your ſelves in the Doctrine of Devils, and in lyes, and would make God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, and the Apoſtles unrighteous? for their was fault in <hi>Cain,</hi> fault in <hi>Balaam,</hi> and fault in <hi>Core,</hi> and fault in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and fault in them that turned the grace of God into wantonneſſe, which were of old ordained for this condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Iude</hi> 4. which condemnation is, that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſſe rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evil, and ſo the Apoſtles taught that their was fault in man, as ye may read <hi>Iude,</hi> and thou haſt taught there is none; ſo then thou art unrighteous, who would make God and the Apoſtles unrighteous, like thy ſelfe, let all that fear God judge of it, who are now come to the judgment Seat before the Almighty God, who have been them that erred from the Apoſtles Doctrine, with it is judged, and are judged, and you muſt have a reward according to your works, and he that comes to life, comes out of his wickedneſſe, and not the wicked man enters into the kingdom of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and the promiſe is to the ſeed, and he that works iniquity departs from the ſeed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. And the Election obtaines it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7. Not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171845:21"/>him that wills, nor runs, But God that ſhewes mercy; And whereas thou ſayeſt the wicked manis ordained to life, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe in the Creature, leſs or more, This is juſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Doctrine again, &amp; to bring every one to hide his Talent and none neither to watch nor pray; for this is the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that brings him to lay a ſide wickedneſſe, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from ſin and iniquity, which lets him ſee it, and covetous and drunkenneſſe ſo through the obedience of the Spirit, and that is in the Creature that brings him to confeſſe his ſin, and for ſake it, whereby mercy is ſhewed; the power of God worketh in us ſaith the Apoſtle; And as they had been ſervants to unright couſneſs, ſo came to yeeld themſelves ſervants unto righteouſneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. How comes the commands of God to be obeyed, if there be not ſomthing in the creature that cauſe him to obey it? For thou ſayeſt without any cauſe in the creature, why were all theſe expreſſions ſpoken in ſcripture, that they ſhould obey all things that Chriſt commanded, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. And all the ſtatute, and Ordinances ſpoken of in the ſcriptures if there be not ſomething in man to cauſe him to obey it: but thy intent is to make God unrighteous who reſpects no mans perſon, but gives to every man a reward accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to works, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.23. The one as well as the other, and all ſhall appear befor the judgement of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.10. He will judge the world in righteouſneſſe; but there is ſomething in the creature; for every man that cometh into the world being enlightned, whereby he is capable of obeying or diſobeying, and not believing comes to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and in believing he is ſaved, he hath the witneſſe in himſelfe, <hi>John</hi> 3.8. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10 For he that commits ſin is the ſervant of ſin, <hi>John</hi> 8.24. And there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons with God, but whoſoever doth righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is accepted of him, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34, 35. The Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>He perceived God was no reſpecter of perſons, but whoſoever doth wickedly he hates the light, and is condemned, but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth the truth, cometh to the light,</hi> John 3.21. and ſo out of condemnation, ſo thou teacheſt another Doctrine, ſo as I ſaid before, <hi>The promiſe is to the ſeed, the ſeed is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171845:22"/>Chriſt, and Chriſt all and in all,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.28. And all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and wicked men are ſhut out of the Kingdome of God, where no wicked men enters, one nor other, and man muſt be turned again from wickedneſs, before he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>He being asked what he would do with</hi> Quakers, <hi>and he ſaid if he had been a Civil Magiſtrate, he would have thought it good ſervice to have cut off all their heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There ye may all ſee if he be not of <hi>Cains</hi> ſtock, and what an envy proceeds out of his mouth, and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Spirit, and how would he convert them if they were out of the way? and how would he convince them, who would cut off their heads? hath not this proved the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers to be in the truth, and he out of it, and is not the command of Chriſt that ye ſhould love your enemies? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. Now ye may ſee he is out of the command and example, but followed the example of <hi>Cain</hi> the murtherer, and doth not his envie ſhow as much againſt the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates as againſt the the Quakers, becauſe they will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute his malice, and ſlay them for him, and be his exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners? and were not theſe Prieſts as mad againſt the Magiſtrates, (as they are now againſt the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers) at <hi>Dunbar</hi> fight? and would not they have had their heads off? let their Pulpits witneſs, though now they admire their perſons becauſe of advantage, <hi>Jude</hi> 16. Who cannot hold in, but their ſhame muſt be uttered forth, who would ſlay the perſons of men as <hi>Cain</hi> did; ſo wo from the Lord is gone out againſt you, who are envious, and ſtrives to make the people envious, but the life of God is riſen in the hearts of his people, with which they ſhall ſee you all, and the Quakers be out of the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> who be in the light of Chriſt Jeſus the Saviour of the ſoul, in which they come to have a habitation in God, the Saviour of all men, eſpecially of them that beleeve, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. So you that be out of the light be Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, though ye have great habitations in the earth, for <hi>Cain</hi> built a City yet a Vagabond, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>It was asked him of a fore-ordained number to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiruction,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171845:22"/>and for what Chriſt wept over Jeruſalem. He ſaid, as he was humane he mourned, and his Godhead decreed them to Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is a lying Doctrine of the Devil, for after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> came to be converted, as ye may read in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. And many of the Prieſts came to be obedient to the Faith, for all being gone aſtray both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Rom. 3.9. concluded under ſin, the pure, the eternal tendred over them; who had ſtopped their ears, and cloſed their eyes to that which was pure of God in them, that they might have come to that which is pure, and have been gathered under Chriſts wings, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37. who is pure, and ſo have been converted and healed, and have heard with their ears, and have ſeen with their eyes. And as for the word humane, that is not Scripture language, it ſpeaks not that language, and there were converted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and they were pricked to the heart, when that the Apoſtle ſaid, that was both Lord and Chriſt whom ye have crucified, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. (mark ye) here thou mayeſt ſee thy ſelf to be a lyar; for here was of the <hi>Jews</hi> and of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that he had wept over; thou ſayeſt he had ordained them them to Hell (as he was God) which were converted afterwards; ſo thou wouldſt make God unequal, that the Son is not in the Father, and divideth them, that the Son ſhould weep over them, and the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head decree them to Hell, and did not Chriſt command his Apoſtles that they ſhould not depart from <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> and was not the mighty converſion at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> ſo hath not Chriſt wept over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and after was there not a mighty converſion there? And thou ſayeſt he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned them as God to Hell; there thou mayeſt ſee thy ſelf in the Devils Doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. Many thouſands were converted at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which Chriſt wept over, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles departed from thence, where he gave them command to ſtay; ſo ſee thy Doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is damnable, and thou errs from the Scriptures, let thy-mouth for ever be ſtopped: and are not ye found in the ſteps of them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. that Chriſt gives the mark of blind-guides to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171845:23"/>the multitude, unto the Diſciples, which marks were ſuch as the multitude might take notice of, and I beleeve the multitude will take notice of, and know you; firſt ye bind heavy burthens upon mens ſhoulders, ye are ſayers and not doers, and all their works they do to be ſeen of men, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. they love the uppermoſt rooms at feaſts, and the chiefeſt ſeats in the Aſſemblies, greeting in the Markets, ſtands praying in the Synagogues, called of men Maſters, they were ſwearers, they ſhould ſcourge you in their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and perſecute, do not ye put out of your Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues? Chriſt ſhould ſend Prophets and wiſe men among them, and they ſhould perſecute, and put out of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.34. They ſhould ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, and do not ye do ſo that do deny the light, that lighteth every one that cometh into the world? do any come to the Kingdome, but who come to the light, which every man that cometh into the world is enlightned withal? may not the multitude take notice of theſe things, called of men Maſter, ſtand praying in the Synagogues, having long Robes, ſalutations in the Markets, uppermoſt rooms at feaſts, puts out of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and ſwearers, and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>ſwear not at all, Mat.</hi> 5.34. And be ye not called of men Maſter, for one is your Maſter, even Chriſt, and ye all are Brethren; now here is the marks of the blind guides, as ye may read, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. Are they not a company of Swearers, and will they not ſwear for their own advantage? and were not the Prieſts always envious, and falſe accuſers, provoking the Magiſtrates againſt the Diſciples, againſt Chriſt, and againſt Jeſus? did not the Prieſts ſay Jeſus ſhould die for crying againſt them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 26. And were not the Prieſts at work when any of the Saints were murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſtir up the multitude againſt them, or the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates? Was not the chief Prieſts and Elders ſeeking falſe witneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out Jeſus to death? <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39. And did not the High Prieſts ſay he had ſpoken blaſphemy? it was <hi>Pilate</hi> that put him to death, did not the chief Prieſts perſwade their multitude to ask <hi>Barrabbas, Matth.</hi> 27.20.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171845:23"/>and crucifie Jeſus, and did not they mock him? See how the Prieſts were alwayes buſie for blood, that all the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous blood might come upon them, ſhed upon the earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.35. And did not the Prieſts give money to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> to betray Chriſt? and did not the Prieſts give large money to the Souldiers to tell a lie, and ſay his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſtole him away by night? <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.11, 12, 13. had not <hi>Paul</hi> authority from the High Prieſt to perſecute? <hi>Acts</hi> 9.1, 2. and ſo get you your Authority from the Magiſtrates, and the people their Authority from you to perſecute, and would not the chief Prieſts have mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered <hi>Paul</hi> afterwards, when he was converted, <hi>Acts</hi> 23. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.7. Did not a company come with ſwords and ſtaves from the Prieſts with <hi>Judas</hi> to take Chriſt? <hi>Mark</hi> 14.13. as a troop of Robbers wait for a man; ſo doth a company of Prieſts murther in the way by conſent, and have not ye conſented together? <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.2.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>That Chriſt ſcorned men when he bad them be perſect becauſe he knew it was impoſſible for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is wickedneſs and impudency to ſay Chriſt ſcorned men when he bad them be perfect. This is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and the Devils Doctrine, for to ſay that Chriſt did command that which men ſhould not come to, for Chriſt nor God commanded nothing but what ſhould be attained unto, and it will be attained unto, and hath been attained unto; Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Be perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect, Mat.</hi> 5.4. he knew that they might be perfect if they come into the Kingdom of God, for there no unperfect thing muſt enter, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and ſo he did ſpeak that which he knew people ſhould come into, but they ſhould come into it, if ever they came into the Kingdome of God; what is this to thee which cannot love enemies? for they that love enemies ſhall know perfection, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect love and patience have its perfect work, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.4. the Apoſtles ſpeak wiſdome to them that were perfect, but not the worlds wiſdome which comes to nothing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. and the work of the Miniſtry was for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints, till they all come into the unity
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171845:24"/>of the faith, unto the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, and unto the meaſure and ſtature and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. and they ſhould not be any more toſſed to and fro with the windy Doctrines of men, nor cunning craftineſs wherewith they lie in wait to deceive, and there art thou toſſed up and down with every wind, and far off the work of the miniſtry, when thou ſaiſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly, <hi>Chriſt ſcorned men when he bad them be perfect;</hi> Chriſt did not ſcorne them, but thy doctrine, it is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and thou and you that tranſgreſs and abide not in the doctrine of Chriſt, thou and you are Anti-chriſts, as ye may read, 2 <hi>John</hi> 9.10.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>When it was asked him, of the words that Peter ſpake of, concerning them that brought in damnable Hereſies, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the Lord that bought them, he ſaid they did but think the Lord had bought them, but they were not bought, but they thought they had been ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here thou again with thy damnable Doctrine, doſt go about to make <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> lyars, who ſpeaks contrary to ſcripture, and perverts their Doctrine, and the words of <hi>Peter</hi> are thus, even denying the Lord that bought them; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. and the words of <hi>Jude</hi> 4. denying the onely Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and thou ſaiſt the Lord had not bought them, but they thought he had bought them, wo and miſery, man, will be thy portion, that thou ſhould ſo wickedly pervert the Apoſtles Doctrine and Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.10. and bring in ſuch damnable Doctrine, and devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Doctrine, and ſpeaks ſuch lies in hypocriſy, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is ſeared with a hot Iron, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. it is time for people to turne away from you, who have ſo long deceived them.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>Concerning theſe words of</hi> Ezek. 18.28. <hi>If the righteous man turn away from his righteouſneſs, his former righteouſneſs ſhall be no more remembred; and he ſaid the meaning of that ſcripture was, they thought they had been righteous, but they were not, but ſuppoſed it had been ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here in this thou art a miniſter of unrighteouſneſs, thou goeſt about to make God a lyar, and the Prophets,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171845:24"/>and perverts the ſcriptures, for if he forſakes his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and commits ſin and iniquity, and treſpaſſes, he ſhall die, and not live in the righteouſneſſe; but if he forſake his ſin, treſpaſſes and tranſgreſſions, in the righteouſneſſe that he hath done and doth, he ſhall live; ſo Gods wayes are equal, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. And thou ſayeſt they thought they had been righteous, but it was not ſo: And the Lord by the Prophet ſaith it was ſo, that they ſhould live in their right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſſe, and dye if they depart from it, and tranſgreſſed here thou art a diminiſher from the Prophets and Apoſtles words, whoſe name is diminiſhed out of the book of life, read <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.19.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>He denyed that Chriſt dyed for all men, but for the Elect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Contrary to <hi>Johns</hi> Doctrine, who ſaith, he is the propitiation for our ſins, and not for our ſins onely, but for the the ſins of the whole world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. and ſo it is the unbeliever that is ſhut out; and not believing in the light that men are enlightened withall, with which light they might ſee the one offering, who taſted death for every man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. and doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, that all through him might believe; and they that believe not in the light are condemned, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18. but believing in the light, ſhall come out of condemnation, and he is the Saviour of all men, but eſpecially of them that believe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. and the grace of God which brings ſalvation hath appeared to all men, which was the ſaints Teacher, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12. and they that turn it into wantonneſſe, ſhall with it be condemned <hi>Jude</hi> 4. and they that ſet up a heap of teachers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. after their own luſts, and went out from the Apoſtles doctrine, before the Apoſtles deceaſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. and have turned the grace of God that brings ſalvation, into wantonneſſe, ever ſince, and ſaith it hath not appeared unto all men, which brings ſalvation, which is ſaving grace, and Chriſt Jeſus doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every man that cometh into the world, that they might believe, and walke after him, and ſaith, they that follow him ſhall not abide in darkneſſe, but ſhall become the children of light, and have the light of life, <hi>John</hi> 8.12.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171845:25"/>Now ſay they that hate the light, it is not ſufficient, it is not a ſaving light, but they ſhall find it ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demme them, and their unbeliefe, for not believing in it; for believing in it, they come to have the light of life, <hi>John</hi> 8.12 and <hi>John</hi> 12.36.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>He being asked who were hirelings, if they were not that did take hire? his anſwer was, they were hirelings that did not take hire, and to prove it, he brought that ſcripture in Philipians of them that preached Chriſt of envy and ſtrife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now all may ſee what doctrine he brings, to pervert or reſt the ſcriptures, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.15. to prove them hirelings that do not take hire, that in the <hi>Philipians</hi> doth not prove that they were hirelings, neither did they take hire: ſo that for his purpoſe makes nothing, though for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he brings that ſcripture, but that his folly and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe might appeare, and be made manifeſt by the light, for now to it his deeds are come, who is unfit to talke of the ſcripture.</p>
               <p>Pr. <hi>He ſaid it was the cleare mark of the Devil to go up and down from place to place to preach as the Quakers doe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now here in this he may charge all the prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which went up and downe from place to place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. that this is the marke of the Devill, but this is too manifeſt to bring to light, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Presbyterian Prieſts of Scotland, who lies in Dens and Corners, and fat benefits, and there ſtick in the earth, and are crept into houſes, who ſay it is the Devills marke to go up and downe to preach; but this is that they may manifeſt themſelves to be judged by the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that their folly might appear unto all men, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.5.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. likewiſe the Presbyterian Prieſt are turned like ranters, who ſaith whatſoever man doth, God hath a hand in doing of it, whether Good or Evil, if a man commit never ſo much ſinne, and live never ſo wickedly he ſhall go to Heaven if he be ordained there to come; how was God greived when <hi>David</hi> ſinned? the Lord was angry; the Lord was wrath, when the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſinned againſt him, it greived the Lord that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171845:25"/>he had made man, when all fleſh had corrupted his way, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6. and thou and you go about to make God the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſin, and ſaith God hath a hand in it, whatſoever a man doth here: again you and thou be in the doctrines of Devils, what ſhall we ſay that God is the author of ſin? God forbid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. they that tranſgreſſe the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, provoke him to anger, and though God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the evil, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.7. yet his commandments was to man, that he ſhould not go into it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. but when he did, he tranſgreſſed the command of God; ſo he who ſaith if ye murther, God is the author of it, if ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, God is the author of it, if ye do unrighteouſly God is the author of it: you that murther, perſecute, and do not righteouſly, are of him that kept not the command of God, of whom ye are, <hi>Joh.</hi> 44. that would perſecute and murther, thou art gone out of the command of God, and joyned with the Devil, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. that went out of the truth, the Devil he went out of his eſtate, and the woman hearkned to him, and went out of her eſtate, and man to the woman, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. The Jews went out of their ſtate, when they perſecuted, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.25. <hi>Cain</hi> went out of his ſtate, when he murthered, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. The Chriſtians went out of their eſtate, fince the daies of perſecution, who had the name of Chriſtianity; <hi>Cain</hi> went out of his ſtate when he murthered, and <hi>Balaam</hi> went out of his ſtate, when he coveted the wages of unrighteouſneſs, and admired mens perſons, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. <hi>Jude</hi> 11. <hi>Core</hi> went out of his ſtate when he gain-ſaid the truth, <hi>Num.</hi> 16. <hi>Jude</hi> 11. the falſe Prophet, and the Antichriſt which is the Beaſt, and the mother of Harlots, went forth from the ſtate of the Apoſtles, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. which hath been fince the daies of the Apoſtles, and ſo all wars, and fightings, and adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, is becauſe of being out of the truth, fallen out of it, <hi>James</hi> 4. there is pride and Lucifer, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14. and that is it that is of old ordained to condemnation, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. and to be kept down, and to be condemned everlaſtingly; and there the time that ſhall be witneſſed fit for the fire, and Death and Hell; and the falſe Prophet, and the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171845:26"/>and the Serpent caſt into it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.14. but leaven is known that leavens into the new lump, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. the everlaſting fire that burns for ever, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.46. how are the profeſſions, formes, and religions fallen from the ſtate, and loſt the ſtate, and out of the ſtate that Chriſt was in, the Prophets were in, <hi>Abraham</hi> was in, <hi>David</hi> was in, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Apoſtles was in; and remains in a form of their words, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. and murthers them that enjoys their life, and perſecutes them; The Devil abode not in the truth, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> abode not in the truth, but tranſgreſſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>Cain</hi> abode not in the truth when he murdered <hi>Abel, Gen.</hi> 4. The Jews abode not in the truth, but crucified the juſt, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.6. The Antichriſt, and the falſe-Prophets, ſince the daies of the Apoſtles, and the Beaſt abode not in the truth, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.19. that made the war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. And here is the murderers, envious, and perſecutors, warring, and fighters, and their ſacrifice God never accepted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.5. in all ages: and theſe are them that perſecuted thoſe that was in the truth, whoſe ſacrifice God accepted, to the witneſs of God in you all I ſpeak; that you may ſee your fall from the truth, out of the Prophets life, Chriſts life, and the Apoſtles life; ſo be out of the commands, and fallen from God, and ſay that none can keep the commandments: that is the Word that ſhall ſtand for ever, ſo ye are they that loves not not God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.13. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.4. but are of the Beaſt and falſe Prophets that makes war againſt them that keep the commands of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11. ſo that which ſaith, none can keep the Commandements, is fallen out of the truth, and the Commandments of God, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. And to him the truth is death, and the commands of God in which the Saints live, to whom the Commandments are not grievous, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:171845:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Thomas Garwine,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Edenborough,</hi> his Doctrine and PRINCIPLES.</head>
               <p>Pr. <hi>THat the Childe that is not ſprinkled with outward wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is in a damnable ſtate, and worſe then an infidell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now here he and the reſt of the Presbyterian Prieſts of <hi>Scotland</hi> may ſay <hi>Abraham</hi> was in a damnable ſtate, <hi>Iſaac</hi> was in adamnable ſtate, <hi>Jacob</hi> was in a damnable ſtate, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> was in a damnable ſtate, and <hi>David</hi> was in a damnable ſtate, and <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt was in a damnable ſtate, which were not ſprinkled by a Prieſt with outward water, nor named by the Prieſt, ſo thou and you with your tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that ſay a Child is in a damnable ſtate, if ye do not ſprinkle it with water; and the Apoſtle bids them not look at the things that are ſeen, and you are in the damnable ſtate, and the damnable doctrine, teachers of lies; and many ſimple people have been deceived by you, and given over to believe you, but God hath taken the vail off their hearts, that you begin to be ſeen: and their ſalvation ſhall they know ſtands not in elements, as though you, with your ſprinkling Infants with outward water, could bring out of the damnable ſtate; Oh ye deceivers, did not the Apoſtle ſay, they that were Circumciſed, Chriſt profited them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2 ye have long deceived people with your beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly rudiments, and elements, and doctrines, and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. hatched up at Schools, and never commanded of God; and ſay, if people will not obſerve your traditions, or your elements which you call (a Papiſt word) Sacrament, and periſhing, they not obſerving it, are in a damnable ſtate, and worſe then the Heathen and Infidels; an Infidel, is an Heathen, one that knowes not God; But your genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſays it is blaſphemy to ſay any hath known God, and hath ſeen God, and ſpoken to God: ſo they themſelves have concluded to be Heathen: The Heathen know not God: The Heathen obſerves traditions; and they that know
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171845:27"/>God cannot obſerve the traditions of the Heathen: but obeys the Apoſtles doctrine, and touches not, taſts not, nor handles the traditions of men and Ordinances which will periſh, ſo not ſaying; ſo they that obſerve not traditions are not worſe then Heathens: but they that obſerve traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are as the Heathens, and be out of the Apoſtles doctrine in their own traditions and rudiments, and are offended at thoſe that will not touch them. <hi>Robert Semple</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Laſmahagow</hi> came to <hi>George Weare</hi> of <hi>Saffield</hi> to reaſon with him, and he laid down theſe following things for his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and principles, His firſt doctrine and principles was to prove the lawfulneſſe of being called of men maſter; ſtanding praying in the Synagogues, going in long Robes, and he mentioned <hi>Ezras</hi> Pulpit of wood upon which he ſtood, and read the Law to the people; and for the reſt he ſaid nothing, for his mouth was ſtopt concerning theſe things, being found in the ſteps of the Phariſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. we do grant that <hi>Ezra</hi> had a Pulpit of wood, but you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your ſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel and plesbyterians, and are ye ſain to run to <hi>Ezra,</hi> in the Law for a Pulpit? now you have ſhewed your ſelves what you are; and brought your deeds to the light; but the Prieſthood was made by the Law of God: ſo were you never; that prieſthood changed, and the Law changed alſo by which it was made, and pulpit and Tythes ended; and Chriſt the everlaſting Prieſthood witneſſed; ſo thou and you have proved your ſelves no Miniſters of the Goſpel, Chriſt Jeſus, the power of God, and the wiſdom of God, the ever laſting Prieſt-hood, who is the end of Prieſts, Pulpits and Tythes, that was true in their place. So you that have got up another Pulpit, Tythes, Temple, like Readers of the Law, and not like miniſters of the Goſpel, and Prieſts, are ſeparated from the Apoſtles in the deluſion, and from Chriſt the everlaſting Prieſthood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. and are them that <hi>Jude</hi> 19. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. ſpeakes of, That ſeparates themſelves, having not the Spirit that they were in who witneſſed againſt Pulpit, Tythes, and Prieſt-hood, and witneſſed Chriſt the everlaſting Prieſt-hood, which Pulpit, Tythes, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171845:27"/>Prieſthood ye are crying up, and ſo Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Weare</hi> bad him prove his practice for ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Infants, and whether or no they were not to believe before they were Baptized. He ſaid the promiſe was to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed; <hi>George</hi> anſwered him, it was not to ſeeds, as to many, but to thy ſeed which is Chriſt. <hi>Robert</hi> the Prieſt ſaid, That ſeed Chriſt, was natural, contrary to the Apoſtles doctrine, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. who ſaid Chriſt was the power of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14, 15. and Chriſt the miſtery, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2.7. The firſt man is of the earth earthly, the ſecond man is the Lord from Heaven heavenly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. the ſpirituall man judgeth all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. The ſeed of the woman bruiſeth the ſerpents head, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and the promiſe is to the ſeed, and the ſeed is Chriſt the power of God, And Chriſt the ſeed is the ſpiritual man and ſo not natural, but the Prieſt ſaid the ſeed is natural. Now let all ſee in this whether he be not given up to deluſion, to ſpeak lies in hypocriſy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. to delude and deceive people for diſhoneſt gain, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.13. Which ſeed he and all the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians ſhall finde ſpiritual to judge them, and bruiſe the heads of them, and break their wicked cords and bonds of iniquity which they have laid upon the people, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. <hi>Acts</hi> 15. The day is at hand that their judgement is come; by that man whom God hath ordained, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. and to judge the world in righteouſneſſe, and to give to every man a reward according to his works, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 62.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. who ſhall give to him an account for every idle word they ſhall ſpeak in the day of judgement, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36. And <hi>William Kenedie</hi> came to <hi>George Weare,</hi> and promiſed him that he ſhould have a publick hearing, he hearing what the Prieſt and the reſt of the Elders charged him withall, And when he came they would not give him a hearing; and ſo found them truce-breakers that are to be turned away from, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and ſuch as creep into houſes, and be of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, boaſters, proud, high-minded, as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> who have a forme of godlineſs, and denys the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171845:28"/>power, which are to be turned away from: And after that the ſaid Prieſt did excommunicate <hi>George Weare</hi> in in another pariſh without any hearing, nor would not let him know for what they excommunicated him, which was a work of darkneſſe to make the peoples minds envious againſt the juſt: upon which <hi>George Weare</hi> went to their meeting place to read a paper to him, to ſhew why he denyed him; and two Prieſts, <hi>Robert Semple,</hi> and <hi>John Hume</hi> being there, bad the people to knock down that excommunicated (Swinger) which is in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh (Rogue) upon which the people did obey the Prieſt, and did beat, and knock <hi>George Weare</hi> down to the ground; and might have murthered the man, had not the Lords mercy been ſeen, ſo they be in <hi>Cains</hi> way, in envy; <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>Jude</hi> 11. And <hi>George</hi> got up again, and the Prieſts bad the people ſtrike him; and they did beat him, and pluck him by the hair of the head; and the Prieſts bad beat them away; and they did ſo. And after the Prieſt ſummoned <hi>George</hi> to the Court; and told the Bayliff he would prove it by the Scripture, he muſt be ſtoned to death; now here is the murthering <hi>Jewes</hi> nature, that ſtoned the prophets, and ſtoned the Apoſtles; and ſtoned <hi>Steven,</hi> and took up ſtones to ſtone Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.24. <hi>John</hi> 8.59. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.58 And bloody Butchers, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayers, no Miniſters of Chriſt: did not the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets go alwayes with the beaſt to war? <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. againſt Saints and the Lamb; and did not the cheif prieſts ſtir up the rulers againſt Chriſt, and had not the prieſts a hand to murther? and was not the prieſt at the examination of <hi>Steven,</hi> and the Councel gave order that he ſhould be ſtoned to death? and did not the Prieſts ſtir up the Rulers and Magiſtrates, though they themſelves did not often do it, which had not the power, but they ſtirred up the Magiſtrates to do it? And they came to be their ſlaughterers, to execute their malice, and be their executioners; ye do not, ye may ſay, it is the Magiſtrates which ye ſtir up to do it. It is not ſaid, the Prieſts did ſlay and crucifie Chriſt, but <hi>Pilate,</hi> but the Prieſts had
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171845:28"/>power amongſt the multitude to perſwade the multitude to aske the murderer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. (which had murther in their hearts) and <hi>Pilate</hi> did the thing; and did not God overthrow <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and deſtroy the power of the Magiſtrates there, and prieſts both? and hath not God done it in many ages for executing the Prieſts malice, and their envy againſt the juſt, and his anointed? have not ye many examples ſet down in the ſcripture, which ye may all take notice of it.</p>
               <p>Therefore take heed all ye Magiſtrates, how you execute and avenge the malice and wickedneſs, and envy, of any one againſt the juſt: for the envie of the envious, and the wickedneſs of the wicked ſhall ſlay himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.21. and the righteous ſhall ſee it. Therefore you that are called Chriſtian Magiſtrates, execute not, neither be ye executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of their madneſs, and envy of thoſe who calls them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Miniſters of Chriſt. That would have you to ſlay, to ſtone, to ſtocks, to priſon, and to put to death them that be contrary to them; thoſe be murtherers in <hi>Cains</hi> way, man-ſlayers, wraſtlers againſt fleſh and blood, and not Miniſters of the Goſpel which ſaith, Love enemies, and render to no man evil for evil, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. and this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from the Scribes and Phariſees who loved their own, and perſecuted others, and ſtoned others, and drew the Magiſtrates to do it, which ſaith the Miniſters of Chriſt, we wreſtle not with fleſh and blood, but againſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and powers, and ſpiritual wickedneſſes in high places, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12. Now thoſe Miniſters that would have the perſons of men ſlain, are like <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Jezabel,</hi> the beaſt and falſe Prophets, that ſlew <hi>Abel, Gen.</hi> 4.1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. the perſons of men ſtoned, impriſoned, and put to death, are as the Jewes Prieſts, and thoſe Magiſtrates that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes their malice, are as the Jews Magiſtrates, unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Magiſtrates. And ſo thoſe are they that are wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſtoning, ſtriking and impriſoning againſt fleſh and blood. And in the mean time ſpiritual wickedneſs rules among them, and rulers of darkneſs in high places, where fleſh and blood are wreſtled againſt; ſo in this ſtate both
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:171845:29"/>Miniſtry and Magiſtracy are blind, that be out of the fear of God; they turn their ſword backward, whilſt they are executing the Prieſts malice, and the Prieſts will ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the hands of evil doers; and provoking to ſlay, and againſt fleſh and blood wreſtling, and do not profit the people at all, and ſtirres up the multitude againſt the juſt; that he may keep himſelf in his place for his own ends, and admiring the Magiſtrates perſons, and mens, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of advantage, <hi>Jude</hi> 16. &amp; reſpects their perſons, which ſhews they be out of the faith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. which gives victory over the world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4. and out of the doctrine of Chriſt and the Apoſtles; now the Magiſtrates is for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well: which walks in the life, which he that doth evil goes from; where the rulers of darkneſs and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual wickedneſſes are; and this Magiſtrate he can ſee, he turns not the ſword backward, he anſwers that of God in every one; and is for a praiſe to them that do well, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. ſo every evil doer acts contrary to that of God in them; now a Miniſter of Chriſt wreſtles not againſt fleſh and blood, but againſt ſpiritual wickedneſſes in high places; ſo every one that doth evil acts contrary to that of God in him, ſo the higher power goes above him; <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. So the higher power is above him, and before he was, all power in heaven and in earth is given to the Son of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.22. above all the powers of the earth, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. but they who does evil, goes from the light, and ſo the higher power goes againſt him. The Magiſtrates that be in the power, is a terror to the evil doers that acts contrary to the light wherewith every one that cometh into the world be enlightned, The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates be in that power which goes over him, and is a praiſe to them that be in the light, and the Miniſters of God is to bring from under the occaſion of the Magiſtrates ſword.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Weare</hi> being with his friend ſtanding in the field neer <hi>Foord</hi> meeting-houſe, as they call it, he neither ſpeaking, nor acting any thing againſt any man, but ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171845:29"/>in the fear of the Lord with his friend; <hi>William Lowry,</hi> and <hi>John Hambleton</hi> called Juſtices, committed him to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, where they lay twenty and three dayes; and here is his innocency preached.</p>
               <p>The original righteouſneſs was before the fall; The original of ſelf-righteouſneſs was that which fell, and is in the fall; that tranſgreſſed.</p>
               <p>And in the Catechiſm which is tollerated by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly, and in the Catechiſe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> called, <hi>A Short Catechiſm, They ſay that the Word of God is contained in the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And the Scriptures are writings; and it ſaith, God is the Word, <hi>John</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.27. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, The Heaven of Heavens cannot contain him, and you ſay he is contained in the Scriptures with his writings: and you ſay there is Three perſons; and the Scripture doth not ſpeak of Three perſons, and the Jewes had the Scriptures, and knew not Chriſt, the Word of God: Then ye tell people of an outward ordinary meanes, by which Chriſt Communicates the benefit of Redemption; The word Sacraments; the Scripture doth not ſpeak of Three Perſons, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they are Papiſts words; of them ye have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them; the meanes of ſalvation is not ordinary, or outward; but Chriſt is the ſalvation, who is Eternall, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. and they that come to him, come to the end of the outward, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. Ye ſay the Sacraments are the Effectuall meanes to ſalvation; and ye ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, they are not as they are themſelves: (ſo here is confuſion) but onely by the bleſſing of Chriſt, and his ſpirit in them. How do ye differ from the Papiſts? for they ſay he is in them; and ye ſay his Spirit is in them, and where his Spirit is, is not he? Oh blinde, are ye found out? go ye home to your Mother the Papiſt; where Chriſt Spirit is, he is. And ye ſay your two Sacraments, is Baptiſme, and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. The Scripture doth not call Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper, two Sacraments; which Names you and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171845:30"/>the Papiſts adore and worſhip, which you have given to them; again, you in your Catechize call the Firſt day in the week the Sabbath-day: Where did ever any of the Miniſters of Chriſt, or Chriſtians, un-apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatized call it ſo? are not you come unto the breach, and guilty of your owne judgement? Of the third Commandment, when ye give another Name to the Scriptures, then they give themſelves, in calling them the Word, and calling Baptiſme, and the Supper, the Sacraments? <hi>Exodus</hi> 20. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, God ſpake all theſe words, when he gave forth the Commandements, (mark words) and the words of Chriſt are Spirit and Life, <hi>John</hi> 6.63. God is the Word, <hi>John</hi> 1.1. and Chriſt is the Word, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. and the Word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Fleſh, and dwelt among us, <hi>John</hi> 1.14. And them that had the words of the Scriptures, which cannot be broken, <hi>John</hi> 10.35. the Law and the Prophets; they knew not Chriſt, the Word, before they be brought to the light that Chriſt hath inlightned them with, and they be brought to the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 5.37. <hi>John</hi> 8.19. Can the whole world ſay the Lords Prayer in truth? or was it taught his Diſciples, or to the world? doth not people draw nigh to God with their lips that ſay it, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 20.13. and are not in the light, which every man is lighted, that cometh into the world withall: Can ye ſay the Lords Prayer, which is, <hi>Forgive us our treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſſe againſt us,</hi> without Hypocriſie? How do ye forgive them, when ye would have them perſecuted, and would have them ſtoned, you that be Teachers of the people? and how do ye love your neighbours as your ſelves? and fulfill the Law and the Prophets; <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. to do ſo as you would be done by?</p>
               <p>To ye Presbyterians of <hi>Scotland,</hi> I ſpeak that be teachers, whoſe principles is to ſtone, chop off heads, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them that be contrary minded to you, would ye have thoſe that be contrary to your mindes ſtone you to death, chop off your heads, impriſon, and baniſh you,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171845:30"/>and perſecute, and excommunicate you? This is the Law and the prophets, to do as ye would be done by: as others ſhould do to you, ſo do unto them: but Chriſt who is the end of the Law and the prophets, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. ſaith his doctrine is to love enemies, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. and ſaith, if men perſecute you, pray for them, and bleſſe them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them that perſecute you, and deſpitefully uſe you, that you may be the children of your father which is in heaven: who makes the Sun to ſhine upon the evil and the good, and the rain to deſcend upon the juſt and the unjuſt, if ye love them that love ye, what reward have ye, the Publicans and Phariſees do ſo, and the apoſtatized Chriſtians who are got into the formes of words, but out of the life of the Saints of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and there they are ſaluting their brethren onely, but ſaith Chriſt, be ye perfect as your heavenly Father is perfect, which you ſtand againſt; ſo ye are they that have denyed the one offering which hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected for ever them that are ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. And makes the blood of Chriſt of none effect; which cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from all ſin, and the new Covenant, which blots out all ſin and tranſgreſſion; and all upon the earth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and worſhipers, that call your ſelves Brethern, and Chriſtians, and offerers, of what ſort ſoever, that have but the name, before thou offers be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to thy brother, go leave the gift at the alter, and be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.24. then will the Lord accept thy offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and all upon the earth that prayeth; ſo that ye doe forgive others that treſpaſſe againſt you, as you would have the Lord forgive you your treſpaſſes.</p>
               <p>Oh how is the beauty of the Church of Presbyterians marred, and deformed! oh how are they become Cages of unclean birds, Synagogues of Sathan! Oh how are their Teachers become envious men, and murtherers, of <hi>Cains</hi> Stock, in whom the eternall life is not abide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: That would club, ſtone, and chop off heads of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171845:31"/>ſtrangers, ſervants of the Lord God, and Sonnes, and Daughters, and Excommunicate, and put out of their Synagogues; theſe things have I ſpoken unto you, that ye ſhould not be offended, <hi>John</hi> 16.2. they ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate you, yea, the time cometh, that they that kill you, ſhall think they do God good ſervice; theſe things will they do unto you, becauſe they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew the Father, nor me. Theſe things have I told you before, that when the time comes, ye may remember that I told you of them, <hi>John</hi> 16.4. ſo the ſayings of Chriſt are fulfilled by you that Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, and put out of the Synagogues of the Jewes, ye are like, and theſe are their markes; that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their know the Father, nor the Son of God. Theſe Temples, Pulpits, Prieſts, that are ſet up, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, are amongſt the falſe Prophets that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. and <hi>John</hi> ſaw was come, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18.19. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. which went forth from them, which all the world went after, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.3. And theſe Excommunications, from you are, that none ſhould buy nor ſell, but ſuch as worſhip the Beaſt, and receive his Marks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.14. And it was the Beaſt that would kill and deſtroy, and the Dragon, and the Falſe Prophets, them that kept the teſtimony of Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. here is the patience and faith of the Saints; that by the blood of the Lamb that overcomes, that have the teſtimony of Jeſus, and kept the commands of God; ſo the Jewes excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications which had the true Temple, true Tithes, and true Prieſts, which had the Figure, the Type, Chriſt being come the ſubſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Prieſt-hood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. the everlaſting Covenant, and the one offering, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. ſo them that went from the prieſthood went to Chriſt; The Jewes did excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate them out of the Synagogues; now they did not know the Son nor the Father that did excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, <hi>John</hi> 16. though they had the figures and Types of the Son of God. They held up their outward
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171845:31"/>things; and ſaw not the Son of God the ſubſtance when he was come, ſo theſe knew not the Son of God nor the Father that excommunicated and put out of the Synagogues; which Chriſt bad them that was to be put out of the Synagogues, not be offended at thoſe things; he told them before they came to paſſe, That when theſe things come to paſſe ye may remember that I told you. Now thoſe are they that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come; and the Apoſtles ſaw was come, that went forth from them; which hath got up Tythes, and Temples, and Pulpits, and Prieſts, and the Prieſts are excommunicating out of their Synagogues, and theſe muſt neither buy nor ſell with them, nor eat, nor drink, nor have nothing to do with them, except they will worſhip the beaſt, or his image, and fall down to him; and this is the worſhip of the Beaſt got up ſince the Apoſtles: who apoſtatized from the true Church, and went forth from them, which all the world wondred after and worſhipped, and received his mark and his image; They that buy and ſell, and will let others do ſo with them, that are of them that make war againſt them that keep the teſtimony of Jeſus, and the commands of God, and againſt the Saints and the Lamb; but the Lamb and the Saints ſhall have the victory: But the Lamb of God, the ſeed of God is riſen; the beaſt and the falſe Prophet is taken, which hath long deceived the Nations, <hi>Revelations</hi> 2. The old Dragon, the Serpent, the murderer, the deceiver, the devourer, the Mother of Harlots, <hi>Babylon</hi> which hath made all Nations drunk with her fornications, which hath corrupted the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. which the beaſts, and the falſe Prophets that deceives the Nations, and the Antichriſt, the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; ſay they are come but now: Theſe are deceivers of the Nations; that ſay they come but now; for Chriſt ſaid they ſhould come, and <hi>John</hi> ſaid they were come before his deceaſe, whereby he ſaid he knew it was the laſt time; and in the Revelations he ſaid, all the world went after them, and all Nations have drunk of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171845:32"/>the wine of her fornications, and the Kings of the earth have committed fornications with her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2. (mark the word have) and the falſe Prophets ſay they come but now, and now is the laſt time. And theſe are the deceivers of the Nations that ſay ſo. Now are people but coming from them; and now is the judgement of the great whore come; and now is vials of wrath to be powred upon her that hath corrupted the earth, and now ſhall they go into captivity, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. and 18. And now ſhall people come to that which the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the beaſt, and the Mother of Harlots went from, all theſe heads and horns, and Crowns, will turn againſt others with their tongues, Languages; and <hi>Babylon,</hi> that hath been amongſt them; and now is the ſeed of God riſen, which overthrowes all the excommunicators upon the earth, both beaſt and falſe Prophets and <hi>Jewes</hi> both, which ſeed of God brings to ſee to the beginning. Glory to the higheſt for ever; and <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> beaſts and falſe Prophets, and is at the top of them all, and the corner ſtone is laid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Caſtairs,</hi> and <hi>James Durram</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> when the Faſt was appointed by the Engliſh, they kept their Houſes, and cauſed their ſervants to work, and took notice of all thoſe that countenanced the Engliſh Faſt, and the firſt day they preached, then after they ſaid it was neceſſary that a day of Humiliation ſhould be, and that all people ſhould be humbled for the powers they ſaw now ruling in the land, for they were giving liberty and tolleration to all ſects, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as Anabaptiſts, Independants, and ſaid that the Baptiſts denyed all worſhip and Ordinances, as they were and ought to be according to the Eccleſiaſtical Government, which Government is the true hedge of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lodowick Simerell</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Munkland,</hi> he ſaid before ſeveral perſons that no true Juſtice had been, or was ſince thoſe enemies came to this Nation, neither would be until the Lord remove them in his own time:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:171845:32"/>
                  <hi>Henry Foreſide</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Lenyey,</hi> and if <hi>Paul</hi> had been alive he would have ſtoned the Quakers; and it was Chriſtian zeal to ſtone them; and many friends were ſtoned and beat, and blood is ſhed: thoſe that ſtoned the Apoſtles and Saints, and haled them before judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeats and Magiſtrates; and the chief Prieſts had a hand in putting Chriſt to death, perſwaded them ſo to do, and the cheif Prieſts had a hand in ſtoning of <hi>Steven</hi> to death, and the Prieſt had a hand in caſting <hi>Jeremy</hi> into the dungeon, and into the ſtocks, and ſaid he was worthy of death; and the high Prieſt <hi>Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> examined <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> was exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Prieſt, was put out of the Temple by the Prieſts and Rulers, and charged no more to ſpeak in that name; and ſuch were theſe who had a form of godlineſſe, but denyed the power, and ſuch ever ſtirred up the people to blood and tumults againſt the harmleſs, and innocent in the truth; Therefore come to the light you that have taſted of the power of the Lord God, that with it you may ſee and judge how the Prieſts blinded the Magiſtrates by flattery, and ſo truth came to be their enemies.</p>
               <p>How do you receive ſtrangers, ye Presbyterians of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and obey the commands of God, and the Apoſtles commands, which was, be not forgetful to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſtrangers; for ſome have entertained Angels un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares: when as ye would have the ſervants of the Lord priſoned, and ſtocked, and ſtoned to death, or their heads chopped off? ſo you are them that be in <hi>Cains</hi> way, vagabonds from the Spirit of God, now a vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond hath not a habitation in God, but wanders from the witneſſe of God in him, like <hi>Cain</hi> who built a City, and called it after his Sons name, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>I am the light of the world that lighteth every one that cometh into the world ſaith Chriſt the Saviour of our ſouls, every one going from the light ye be enlightened withall, ye are vagabonds, and have have not a habitation in God; and ſo goes into <hi>Cains</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:171845:33"/>way, envious and would ſlay; <hi>Balaams</hi> and <hi>Cores</hi> way, which are with the light condemned; and like unto thoſe <hi>Jewes,</hi> That haled out of the Synagogues, that Chriſt ſpake of that goes in long Robes, and are called of men Maſter, but Chriſt ſaith, be ye not called of men Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, for one is your Maſter even Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſaid they that went in long Robes, loved the chiefeſt places in the aſſemblies; ſhould hale out of the Synagogues, and they that do theſe things be gone from the light, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.2.</p>
               <p>All this perſwading of corrupt Magiſtrates to perſecute them that reprove ſin in the gates, in the Steeple-houſes, ſtreets and highways, is becauſe men have a ſelf-iſh end, and a private intereſt to themſelves, both Profeſſors of Scriptures and Teachers, and them that doth perſecute hath a ſelf-iſh honour, and an intereſt to themſelves, and ſo the ſelf-iſh Profeſſors, Teachers, Magiſtrates that perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes for them; they have a form of godlineſs, but the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs lies ſlain in them, and they matter not for that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; for in that riſing all the deeds, words and actions come to light, and then if the witneſs of God ariſe in them, they will not be offended at ſuch as reproves ſin in their Gates, Markets, Steeple-houſes and Streets; for all upon the earth, while they are from the witneſs of God in them, they are corrupted, and they may get the form of godlineſs, the form of Chriſts, the Prophets and Apoſtles words, and live out of the power, and be in the Religion that is vain, for none upon the earth comes to the power of godlineſs, but firſt they muſt come to the witneſs of God in them, and there is none upon the earth that ever comes to the firſt principle of the pure Religion, but firſt they muſt come to the witneſs of God in them. There's none knows the Scriptures given forth from the power and Spirit of God, which was in the Saints, but firſt they are brought to the Spirit of God in their own particulars. Come all you Officers and Souldiers, now after ye have eaſe, and have overcome your enemies without; take heed leaſt you ſit down in your eaſe and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:171845:33"/>fulneſs, and fall down into the earth, and fleſh, and feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and fulneſs, and pride, and ſo corrupts the earth, and your ſelves, and not come down to the witneſs of God in you; whereby the enemy of God and of your own ſouls might be ſlain, that you might come to find reſt and peace in God, after your outward wars, and ſo come to the inward wars, which takes away the cauſe of the outward, whereby you may all come into true under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to anſwer that of God in every one, for them that do evil, act contrary to that of God in them, to ſuch the ſword is a terror, and a praiſe to them that do well; which is led by the Spirit of God, up to God who is pure, out of the evil: and all Magiſtrates ſwords upon the earth, ſhould reach to that which is pure in every one to the ſoul, ſo it takes away that which wars againſt it, that breaks the outward; ſo comes the ſoul to be ſubject to the higher power, thats above the tranſgreſſor, which all the Magiſtrates and Rulers upon the earth muſt give an account to; and there is none upon the earth that comes to worſhip God in the ſpirit and in truth, but who firſt come to own that of God in them; and there is none upon the earth, that are like to retain God in their knowledge, nor his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, while their minds is reprobated from that of God in them.</p>
               <p>There all may ſee the Covenant of Grace to all men, and the Covenant of light and life with the Father, he gave him for a Covenant of light to the Gentiles, to the Heathen, I will make a new Covenant with the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> the people of God, I will write my Law in their hearts and their mindes, ſo ſaith Chriſt, the Covenant of God, I am the light of the world, and doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, that all men through the light of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God might beleeve it is the Covenant of God, that every man that cometh into the world is enlightned withal, and every one that hates the light wherewith they are enlightned withall, hates the Covenant, and the light
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:171845:34"/>condemns him, and here all men may ſee the free grace of God that brings ſalvation hath appeared to all men; the grace of God that brings the ſalvation, the turning the grace of God into wantonneſs, and walking deſpightfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spirit of grace, they neglect their ſalvation, and bring puniſhment and condemnation upon them, as its written in <hi>Jude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning Election, and what is elected, the grace of God which brings ſalvation hath appeared to all men, the clearing Gods Juſtice, and the fault is in man for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p>There is a precious thing in theſe Scots, but there is a filthy, beaſtly, durty thing lyeth over.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Lodowick Semerell,</hi> Prieſt of the new Steeple-houſe of <hi>Monkeland,</hi> his proceedings towards <hi>Margaret Hambleton.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArgaret Hambleton</hi> went to him to aske the cauſes why he would excommunicate her; he ſaid for three cauſes: Firſt, For that ſhe denyed the Presbytery. Secondly, For denying the Ordinances. Thirdly, For not forſaking the company of ſeducers and hereticks. Her anſwere to the firſt was; your Presbytery, I do deny, becauſe it is tyranical, and hath no power given of God, but what ye take from men; for ye rule as Lords over Gods heritage: The Prieſt ſaid ſhe was ignorant of Scriptures, for they ſpake of the laying on the hands of the Presbytery; ſhe then bid him read the Hebrew copy, which ſaid, the laying on the hands of the Elders, and true Elders that ruled for the Lord I owne, but ſuch as thou that preaches for filthy lucre, that are Covetous, (as <hi>Timothy</hi>) I deny. Secondly, Thy ſaying I deny the Ordinances, is a lie; for all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Jeſus Chriſt I owne, as Preaching, Praying, or Reading, as any is moved of the Lord, ſo to do I own
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171845:34"/>them; for he that miniſtreth out of the ability that God hath given him; or any ſpeaking as the Oracle of God, them I own: and this is according to plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. Thirdly, For that he ſaid, I would not forſake the company of Seducers, and Hereticks: I anſwered, that way thou calls Hereſie, worſhip I the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God: and this is according to plain Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14. And it ſaith, Keep company with them that calls upon God out of a pure heart, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.22. And I know they are the people, therefore thou denies the Scripture, and I obey it; for I witneſſe that Scripture to be fulfilled, <hi>Iſay</hi> 24.5. they have tranſgreſſed the lawes, changed the ordinances, and broken the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant.</p>
               <p>I being gone from home about my outward occaſions, the Prieſt excommunicated me, knowing that I was not there to anſwer him, and he charged all people to have no dealing in the outward with me, when I came home the people ſtood at a diſtance from me, ſo I went to him that I might have the firſt dealing with himſelf, and paid him ſome money that my husband owned him, and he received it from my hand, then I askt him the cauſe why he bid the people have no dealings with me; yet he himſelf was the firſt; but all his anſwer was, ſaying to his man, put her to the dore; then I asked what evill I had done, or wherein I had offended; ſo I being ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the people, ſhewing them how he was out of the moderation, and out of the bonds of Chriſtian pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice; as I did ſpeak, he cryed the more put her to the door, (although I had paid for apart of the houſe building, and ſo had an intereſt in it) then I told him he was out of the practice of the miniſters of Chriſt, and alſo out of all moderation.</p>
               <p>After that he cauſed a man to make repentance in his Congregation, for ſelling me two pecks of Lint Seeds: And ſoone after the Prieſt himſelf came to me to borrow a book which I lent him, then I asked him why he made the man make repentance for that which
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:171845:35"/>he himſelf did practice; he replyed, it was for eating and drinking with me, for he ſaid, The Scripture for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids to eat and drink with an excommunicated perſon; but I ſaid, the Scripture ſaith, The Drunkard, the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator, the Extortioner, the Covetous, and the Idolater, with ſuch a one, eat not; I asked him if I was ſuch a one, he ſaid, I neither can, nor will ſay ſo of you, but I could be content you ſhould live beſide me all dayes of my life (without excommunicating you) if the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry would ſuffer me, and ſo is judged out of his own mouth, to act contrary to his Conſcience, and to be a man-pleaſer.</p>
               <p>Afterwards he preached lies to the people, ſaying, That the Quakers received money from the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſaid, that was the cauſe that ſo many went from their Church; then I and ſeveral Friends went to taxe him for his lye, but he hid himſelf, ſo that he would not come to us, ſo is found a worker of darkneſs out of the Light of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Cauſes laid down by the Prieſts why they excommunicated Friends.</head>
               <p>THe Cauſe why they excommunicated <hi>William Osburne</hi> is this, Becauſe he declared the Miniſters of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Enemies to Chriſts Kingdome and Goſpel, which are blood-thirſty men, and bore his Teſtimony againſt one of them, which by violence the Prieſts were placing in his Land, whoſe name is <hi>William Sterling,</hi> they put him vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently out of his own ground, and for theſe reaſons excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis Simerel</hi> Prieſt of New <hi>Monkeland,</hi> for theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Margaret Hambleton</hi> denied the power of their Presbiter: Secondly, Becauſe ſhe would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171845:35"/>the company of the people of God whom they call Quakers, Seducers and Hereticks, and alſo for denying their Ordinances which are by their own wills, therefore they excommunicated her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Neſmith</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Hambleton,</hi> excommunicated <hi>John Huchiſon,</hi> and would give him no reaſons for what he did it; neither is there any known, except it be for owning the people of God called Quakers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Hume</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Leſmahagow,</hi> and <hi>William Simerel</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Petenace,</hi> with the reſt of the Presbytery at <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerick,</hi> did excommunicate <hi>George Weare</hi> becauſe he harboured the Quakers, and for the denying the power of their Presbytery, and after they had excommunicated him, <hi>Robert Semple</hi> Prieſt of that Pariſh, <hi>viz. Leſmaha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow,</hi> ſent <hi>Andrew Clealand</hi> Conſtable, to tell <hi>George Wear,</hi> if he would give ſatisfaction to the Kirk, they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him in again upon eaſie terms, <hi>&amp;c. George Wear,</hi> ſaid, becauſe they could not ſhew him the way to God, which his ſoul breathed after, who had been long enough under them, he could not own them; and when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable told the Prieſt what he had ſaid, the Prieſt ſaid, If it be ſo with him yet, I proteſt to God we will make him Winter and Summer without.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Mitchel, John Mitchel, Robert Tod, Mary Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Elizabeth Lappey, Marian Mitchel,</hi> did <hi>Peter Kid,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Douglaſs,</hi> with the reſt of the Presbytery of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerick,</hi> did excommunicate them for theſe reaſons as followeth:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Prieſt:</hi> You teach that every man and woman gets ſufficient light from Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ:</hi> Which is according to <hi>Johns</hi> Doctrine, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. who ſaith Chriſt hath lightned every one that cometh into the world, which light is ſufficient to as many as beleeve in it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Pr:</hi> You cry down Miniſters, and ſay there is no need of preaching.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ:</hi> Not of envious murderers, blood-thirſters, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous hirelings.</p>
               <p n="3">3: <hi>Pr.</hi> You deſtroy the Communion of the body and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171845:36"/>blood of the Lord, ſignified and repreſented by Bread and Wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We which have the ſubſtance, have the end of the ſhadow, and the communion is the end of the ſhadow, and of that which is for memory and ſhewes; which is not the body, in which body is the unity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 4. You ſay that the children of God have no ſin in this life, and teach ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Scripture ſays, he that is born of God doth not fin, and is he not a child of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 5. You ſay and teach that the light that Chriſt gives to every one is perfect, and ſo bids them follow the light that is within them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Which is according to Chriſts Doctrine, <hi>Joh.</hi> the 1. and <hi>John</hi> the 3. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Pr.</hi> You deny <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to be the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Scripture ſays the Goſpel is the power of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Pr.</hi> You deny Baptiſme in the Church to be a ſeal of his Covenant, and cry down that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe there is no Scripture for ſprinkling of Infants, but Baptiſme we own.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Pr.</hi> You deny the Lords Day, and would have it taken out of the world, though it be ſet apart in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the Divine Worſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> All days are owned to be the Lords, who is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in Spirit which we own.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Pr.</hi> You go abroad and trouble people in in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We do not trouble them that worſhip God in Spirit, but will-worſhippers, who are in their perſecuting fained humility: Alſo <hi>Thomas Jack, Gabriel Hood, James Cook, Jannet Hambleton, Gawine Scevenſon, John Hambleton, Alexander Hambleton, Barbara Hambleton, Jennet Hambleton, Andrew Hambleton, Jane Hambleton, Katherine Hart, Katherine Hambleton, John Allen, Jane Hambleton, William Hambleton, Margaret Hambleton, John
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:171845:36"/>Hart, Jennet Atkin, John Hart, Alexander Hart, Jane Hart, Gawine Hart, John Lacock, Jennet Brown, Thomas Craiqqe, John Torrens, Katherine Hambleton, Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine Weare, Jennet Wear,</hi> were excommunicated by. <hi>Matthew Mackel,</hi> and the reſt of the Presbytery at <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleton</hi> for theſe cauſes as followeth:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Pr.</hi> You affirm that the Scriptures are not the word of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Scriptures are the words of God, Chriſt is the Word, and the Scriptures are not Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Pr.</hi> You affirm that there is no rule according to which a man ſhould walk, but the rule within him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Spirit is the rule into all truth, and not the Scripture it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 3. You affirm that every man hath a light ſufficient to lead him to Chriſt within him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yea 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. the light that ſhines in his heart, will give him the knowledge of the glory of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 4. You affirm that the Scriptures are not to be preached.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That is falſe, but they are not to be made a trade of by you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 5. You affirm that there is no bleſſing pronounced to the preaching of the word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not to you that make a trade of the words: but they that preach the word has the bleſſing, for Chriſt gives the wo to you, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 6. You affirm that the Miniſtry is no ſtanding Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> VVe affirm that Chriſt muſt preach the Goſpel, but we deny you who preach for filthy lucre, whoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is by man, and not by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 7: You affirm that no man that hath faith, hath ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ:</hi> VVe affirm that faith purifieth the heart, and gives victory over ſin; which faith you ſay is not pure, and curſes them that ſays it is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 8: You affirm that there is no external means to be followed in order to ſalvation.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:171845:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That which is the means to ſalvation is eternal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 9. You affirm theſe to be Miniſters of the man of ſin, and reprobates concerning the faith: that ſayes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt a man is on the earth, he cannot be ſet free from ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We ſay, yea we do ſo, which is according to the Apoſtles Doctrine which ſays they were made free-from ſin, and they ſpake wiſdome to them that were perfect, and they were ſanctified.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 10. You affirm no Sabbath Day to be obſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Neither do you your ſelves, but what you invent, and you do not keep that well neither, but Chriſt the Sabbath we own.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 11. You are deſerters of all publike Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Ordinances of Chriſt we are not, but mans Inventions we are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 12. You rail againſt the Diſpenſers of publike Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and thoſe that countenance thoſe Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Railing we deny, but declaring againſt any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of man we own; and railing is your own, for your Pulpits declares it, that they ſhould neither buy nor ſell, eat nor drink with them in the Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Accuſations were Extracted, and Subſcribed by the Prieſts Clark in this manner following:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. John Bonave.</p>
               <p>And after the Prieſts had excommunicated the aforeſaid perſons, they cauſed a general Synod to meet at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> and made an Order and publiſhed it in all their Old Maſs-Houſes, That none of thoſe People called Quakers ſhould have any entertainment; and that no people ſhould have any dealing with them in any civil affairs, not to give curſed men work, (as they ſtiled our Friends) and hindering men to work for them, and that under the pain of Excommunication. The extent of which Order is, That they ſhould neither buy nor ſell, eat nor drink with them in the Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Kid,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Dauglaſs,</hi> ſummoned <hi>William Michell</hi> and <hi>Robert Todd</hi> to their Presbytery at <hi>Leanarick;</hi> and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:171845:37"/>when <hi>William Michel</hi> appeared before them, him whom they called Moderator, whoſe name is <hi>William Jack,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Carlook,</hi> commanded him to take off his Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net; and when he refuſed, <hi>Richard Gollon,</hi> Bayliff of the Town, who ſate amongſt them to execute their malice, roſe up in rage, and took it off his head, and the Prieſts would not let him give it him again; but keeps it ſtill from him: and he ſtaying in Town all night, and a friend of his, called <hi>Richard Ray:</hi> the Prieſt and Bayliff of the Town came about the tenth hour of the night to the Inne where they lay, and charged the people of the houſe to put them out, notwithſtanding they kept one of their Bonnets, and the night was very ſtormy: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of this, <hi>James White, Agnas Forreſt.</hi> And here is the Prieſts fruits.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Kidd</hi> ſummoned <hi>William Michell,</hi> and <hi>Mary Engliſh</hi> to the quarter Seſſions at <hi>Hambleton,</hi> but did not appear to lay any thing to their Charge: when they came back againe, <hi>Mary Engliſh</hi> went to him, and asked him why he ſummoned them, and did not appear to make known what he had againſt them, but he anſwered not one word; but his wife and ſervants beat, and abuſed her cruelly: Here is your fruits again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stockdale,</hi> and <hi>John Boweran,</hi> being moved of the Lord to declare the truth in the Market-place of <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>havan</hi> on a Market-day, were cruelly abuſed, and many times knockt down with ſtaves, and ſtones, and violently drawn out of the town by the wicked people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stockdale,</hi> and <hi>John Gill,</hi> with many others, having a Meeting in the <hi>Grave-Yard</hi> in <hi>Strahavan,</hi> on a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-day, a company of the Prieſts Hearers came, and fell upon them with ſtaves, and ſtones, and broke up the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtoned them above a quarter of a mile out of the Town inſomuch, that ſome blood was ſpilt, and many was ſore bruiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Iſmead,</hi> for bidding <hi>James Neſmith,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Hambleton,</hi> prove himſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt, was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the Bayliff, and was impriſoned in the Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booth
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:171845:38"/>of <hi>Hambleton,</hi> and after was ſcarryed to a Juſtices Court at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> who commanded him to be ſet in the Stocks, and a Gag put in his mouth, and a Paper pinned on his Breſt; and made an Order for him to depart the Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stockdale</hi> being moved of the Lord to go to the Steeple-houſe of <hi>Damanoy;</hi> and as he ſtood in the Yard declaring the Truth, and againſt their Idolatrous Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the Prieſt came, who did encourage the people to beat him; whereupon ſome of his Elders, and other wicked people, violently knokt him down, and ſet their feet upon him, and plucked much hair off his head, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſome people cried he is kild: and if the power of the Lord had not born him up, which bears up the heads of his Lambs, whom he ſends forth in the midſt of Wolves, when they are perſecuted: he had died amongſt them, for he was not able to ſpeak, neither to riſe, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time after, off the ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Jack,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Carlook,</hi> ſaid to the people of <hi>Liſmahagow</hi> in his preaching, as followeth: <hi>Beloved, If you will contribute, and ſome of you give a ſix pence, and others a ſhilling, that the Steepping may be greater; then God and we will meet, and finde you out ſome honeſt man.</hi> (Mark) the Prieſt will not meet with their God, till they know of a great Steepping.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Wear,</hi> and ſome others, having their Bonnets ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them when they were at a meeting, neer unto the Steeple-houſe of <hi>Leſmahagow,</hi> and he laying it before <hi>William Lowery</hi> called Juſtice, who ſaid, How durſt you come there to keep your meeting; if ever your come there again, I will have you ſcourged, or I will ſcourge you my ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Neſmith</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Hambleton,</hi> cauſed <hi>William Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> to be put into priſon for ſpeaking to him in the Steeplehouſe-yard, where he remained four days in a place where he could ſcarce get room to lie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Pinder,</hi> for ſpeaking in the Steeple-houſe yard of <hi>Kilbryde</hi> between the Prieſts preaching, was carried by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:171845:38"/>the Conſtable before <hi>James Steward</hi> of <hi>Caſtle-Town</hi> called Juſtice, who cauſed him to be put in the Tolebooth of <hi>Rugland,</hi> where he remained about four days, and after that he, to wit, <hi>James Stewart</hi> and <hi>Will. Simmons,</hi> both Juſtices, cauſed him to be ſet in the ſtocks at <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryde</hi> on a firſt day; and ordered him to be carried from Conſtable to Conſtable till he come to his outward abode in <hi>England,</hi> and he being brought to a Conſtable called <hi>John Barrie,</hi> and he being willing of himſelf to go, <hi>Jo. Barry</hi> gave him the Order, and he went into <hi>England,</hi> yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the Juſtices, to wit <hi>James Stewart,</hi> and the reſt fined <hi>John Barry</hi> 10 ſhillings <hi>ſterl.</hi> for doing ſo, and he not willing to pay it, they put him into priſon, where he lay four hours, and a mad man was put in with him, that had a naked knife in his hand, whereby he was in danger of his life, if the Lords providence had not been great in preſerving of him; and the Juſtices when he was brought before them again ſaid, They would forgive him his Fine, if he would not be a Quaker, who anſwered, I cannot tell what I will be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Mitchel</hi> for taking of a Wife contrary to the Order and Law of the Presbyterian Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whereupon the Prieſt of that Pariſh of <hi>Douglaſs,</hi> called <hi>Peter Kidd</hi> complained to the Juſtices, and cauſed to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon him to the Quarter-Seſſions at <hi>Hambleton,</hi> where <hi>James Hambleton</hi> of <hi>Woodhal</hi> was preſent, and <hi>Will. Mitchel</hi> deſired to be judged according to the Law of God, and the right Laws of the Nation; for we have given in a Declaration of the ſaid Marriage to ſome of you; <hi>Woodhal</hi> ſaid, We will neither judge you according to the Law, nor the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, we have nothing to do with them at this time; we will judge you according to the Law of the Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> by which Law and Judgement he lay in the ſtocks at the croſs of <hi>Hambleton</hi> five hours, and after that was put into priſon, where he remained twenty nine dayes, and they ordered him to pay twenty ſhillings <hi>ſterl.</hi> or elſe to receive twenty laſhes on his naked ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders at the Market-place upon the Market-day in <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleton,</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:171845:39"/>and he being not convinced of the breach of any juſt Law, he would not pay the Fine, neither could they get any to give him the puniſhment which they laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. Then <hi>Gawine Hambleton</hi> of <hi>Raploeh,</hi> which is Sheriffe of the Shire, and is alſo Juſtice of Peace, and <hi>Iames Hambleton</hi> another of the Juſtices gave an Order to a Captain that was going to <hi>France</hi> with ſome men, to take him out of priſon to carry him to <hi>France;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they took him out, and carried him to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> where he ſhould have been kept in priſon till they had made reddy their Ship: But in the mean while the thing being laid before <hi>George Monk,</hi> he cauſed to examine it, and the thing being contrary to the juſt lawes of the Nation, he was ſet at liberty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The groſſe <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Doctrines of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Prieſts Reproved, That all may ſee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe be worthy to ſuffer, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſuch Doctrines.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>JOhn Sempel,</hi> Prieſt in <hi>Carrick,</hi> his preaching to the people was this: <hi>People</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what would ye hear? I know ye would hear News: What ſhall I fell you, but old</hi> Oliver Cromwell, <hi>who is called Protector, is dead; he could not beguile death, as Pockie as he was? But there is gotten up one in his place whom they call Lord</hi> Richard, <hi>but beware that Catt</hi> Lambert <hi>kill not Lord</hi> Richard.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>John Burnet,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Kilbrid,</hi> ſaid, They had cauſe to curſe the Magiſtrates every morning, and every even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for giving theſe Quakers tolleration; and he ſaid, if there were a Gallowes ſet up in <hi>Kilbryde</hi> pariſh, to hang all that turn from them, ſo many would not turn to be Quakers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Henry Foreſide,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Lemgey</hi> in <hi>Dumbarton-ſhire,</hi> Prayed, that the Lord might never give them reſt, who is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:171845:39"/>the upholders of this liberty, and tolleration; and ſaid, Lord, take away this liberty and tolleration, &amp;c. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of this, that heard him ſay it, <hi>Andrew Gray, Agnus Gray, Hellene Gray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Robert Semple,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Slamanan,</hi> in his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaid, That Chriſts Sheep had neither mark, nor burn, &amp;c. And that God would ſay to the wicked, what have I to you with you ſir, &amp;c. But I trow,<note place="margin">The Prieſt means the Old Maſſe-houſe, and he that puts into his Mouth.</note> he will ſay another tale to the godly; You have keeped my Kirk well, and trowed my Miniſters, go ye up to Heaven yonder ſir, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Lodowick Semerwell,</hi> Prieſt of New-<hi>Monkland,</hi> ſaid, That the Grace of God belonged not to his Doctrine: And this ſame Prieſt cauſed a man to make his Repentance in his Congregation, for ſelling to <hi>Margaret Hambleton</hi> two pecks of Lintſeed; yet the Prieſt himſelf borrowed a book of her, and did not his Repentance, and ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted that his Doctrine had no grace of God in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now ſerious people may take notice how igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, and without cauſe the ſervants of the Lord ſuffer under ſuch, for the Word of Gods ſake, which is as a fire in their bones, againſt all ſuch Doctrines which hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the grace of God in them, nor which the grace of God belongs not unto, as they themſelves confeſſe; and people may conſider likewiſe, what a clamour and cry hath been among the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> by Petitions, and Addreſſes to every power that appeared in the Nation, to eſtabliſh them in ſuch Doctrines, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the grace of God belonged unto; but is mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, and deſtroyers of the Creatures, and would limit the Spirit of God, and Word of God, from declaring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their deceipt; and doth give themſelves to Curſing of them morning and evening, that will not uphold them, and make Lawes for them, to deſtroy the Seed of God: This is not like the Apoſtle of Chriſt, which ſaid, <hi>Curſe not, but bleſſe;</hi> and their weapons were not carnall, but ſpiritual: The Apoſtles had not a gallowes ſet up for thoſe that turned from them, but the time is come that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:171845:40"/>your folly is made manifeſt unto all men, ſo that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deceive the Nations any more, as ye have done.</p>
               <p>Again, the Prieſts of the Presbytery belonging to <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> made a faſt, and excommunicated theſe perſons, <hi>viz. William Gray,</hi> and <hi>James Findly,</hi> and charged people not to let them come into their houſes, commanding them to have no commerſe with them in buying nor ſelling, nor borrowing nor lending; and <hi>James Findly</hi> being a Smith, they charged people that they ſhould not work with him, for if they did they ſhould be excommuica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alſo; and <hi>Henry Foreſide</hi> Prieſt of that pariſh, again told them, that it was acted in the presbytery, that if any work any longer (work that pertaines to the Smiths trade) with <hi>James Findly,</hi> they ſhould be excommni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, and ſhould not parake with any of his Church-Ordinances, as marriage, ſprinkling the children, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of bread and wine: which act ſeveral of the people murmures under, but ſay they muſt obey it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their minds, becauſe they cannot bear the Prieſts wrath. Again, <hi>John Burnett</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Kilbrid,</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his hearers to have no dealings in civil affaires, with theſe people called Quakers, that were excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated; and he ſummoned ſuch to his Seſſions, which had eaten or drunken, bought or ſold with them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring them to make publick confeſſion before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they had given offence in ſo doing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Robert Paul,</hi> one of the Prieſts elders, ſaid he would convert <hi>James Findly</hi> and his doctrine: to convert him by, was this, That the Scripture was the word; And ſecondly, That the Scriptures was God: Thirdly, That the Scriptures is the way to the Kingdom of Heaven, and no other under Heaven: Fourthly, That the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is the Holy Ghoſt that the Father promiſed that he would ſend, that ſhould reprove the world of ſin, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> If he had ſaid that the Scripture is that which teſtifie of theſe things, that doctrine had bin more like to have converted; for the ſcripture ſaith, That the word was in the begining before ſcripture was; and it ſaith that Chriſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:171845:40"/>is the way, and there is no other Name under Heaven by which men ſhall be ſaved but by Chriſt; it doth not ſay that by no other name but the ſcripture, ſo that all ſuch doctrine will pervert people from God, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them to God.</p>
               <p>And the ſame <hi>Robert Paul</hi> ſaid he would reſpect mens perſons, and that he would never be free from fin, neither was it poſſible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How can thou do any other but reſpect perſons, and commit ſin while thou denyes God to be God, and Chriſt to be the way, and would make the ſcriptures both to be God, and the way to God, and would make them the ſpirit, the gift of the Father; but herein thou art blind, and leads none but the blind, and doth pervert, and not convert; for thou art ignorant of that which convinceth the world of ſin yet, which is the Spirit of truth, which the ſcripture teſtifies of; but that thou muſt firſt come to know to convince thee of, and to condemn thy darkneſs, before thou do either convince, or convert any unto God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Gartſore</hi> Prieſt ſaid, they loved God which keeped not his commandements.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Which is contrary to the Apoſtles doctrine which ſaith, If any man ſaith that he loves God, and keeps not his Commandments, he is a lyar, and the truth is not in him; and hereby do we know wee love God, becauſe wee keepe his commandements, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.3, 4. and his Commandements are not grievous, but joyous. And Chriſt ſaith, Why call ye me Lord, and doth not the thing that I command you; ſo that none loves God, but he who keeps his Commandements, and abideth in him; and he that abideth in him ſinneth not, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Kid,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Douglaſſe,</hi> ſaid, Put a man in never ſuch a cloſe place, his ſoule will run like a poſt horſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſheweſt that thou art ignorant of the ſoul, and never knew what it was, nor knowes how to Miniſter to it, nor how to watch over it; But if thou had ſeen thine own condition, thou might have ſaid
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:171845:41"/>that thy vain thoughts and wandring imaginations runs to and fro in the earth, and thy mind is not ſtaid upon God, and art not come to know the firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal of the the time Religion, that which ſhould ſtay thy mind upon God; ſo thou art to wait to be taught, and not to teach.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Simerwell,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Petinance,</hi> ſaid, that Chriſt died for the Elect, and godly people of the world, and not for the Turks and Pagans, and Barbarians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt died for ſinners, according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. And he came to call ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, not the righteous or godly, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.13. And Chriſt died for all, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15. And is the propitiation for our ſins, ſaith the Apoſtle, that was the believers, and not for ours onely, but for the ſins of the whole World; and the Goſpel is to be preached to every Creature, and remiſſion of ſins in his Name, to Turks, Pagans, and Barbarians. So herein thou haſt ſhewed that thou was never made a Miniſter of the Goſpel unto any, neither knoweth what the Goſpel is to be Miniſtred unto; ſo therefore be ſilent, and learn no more to bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme God, and his truth, as thou haſt done.</p>
               <p>Again, Prieſt <hi>Simerwell,</hi> ſaith, Chriſt calls all men every where to repent, but he will not that all ſhould Repent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here thou would make Chriſt a deceiver, and ſo hath manifeſted thy ſelfe to be Antichriſt; what, doth Chriſt call men to do that which he would not have them to do? What, is there any guile to be found in his mouth? would thou go about to turne the truth of the Scriptures into a lye? which ſaith, That God wills that all men ſhould come to the knowledge of the truth, that they might be ſaved: and thou here hath charged Chriſt fooliſhly and falſly, in ſaying that he calls them to do that which he would not have them to do, when he calls all men every where to Repent.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt of the Presbytery belonging to <hi>Glaſcow</hi> ſummoned <hi>James Findly,</hi> and <hi>William Gray,</hi> to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him for Hereſy as they ſay, and when they
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:171845:41"/>appeared, they ſhut the door, and would let none hear their examination; manifeſting themſelves to be in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and afraid to bring their deeds to the Light, left their deceipts ſhould have been laid open, and reproved; but they would not anſwere, untill the doors were ſet open, and all people to here, that would come in: Truth is bold, and ſeeks no Corners.</p>
               <p>They Prieſts affirmed, that the Light which every one is enlightened withall, is naturall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here they manifeſt their ignorance of the life of Chriſt, which is ſpirituall, whoſe life is the light of men, and this is the true light that lighteth every man that comes into the world; and this light is pure, that Chriſt doth enlighten every one withall; and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doth truth, love the Light, and brings his deeds to the light to be proved, and by the Light is lead to life; but every one that doth evill hateth the light, and will not bring his deeds to the light leſt they ſhould be reproved, and ſo the light is his condemnation, <hi>John</hi> 3.18, 19, 20, 21.</p>
               <p>They affirmed, That Chriſt died not for all, contrary to the Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. as aboveſaid.</p>
               <p>They ſay that the Scripture is the Word of God, which is but a Declaration of the Word, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1. And Chriſt his Name is called the Word of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. The Scriptures are words of God, and Chriſt is the Word that fulfils, and ends the words.</p>
               <p>They affirmed, That men and women, and Children, ſhould be condemned for <hi>Adams</hi> Tranſgreſſion, &amp;c. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Scripture, which ſaith, The Children ſhall not bear the iniquity of their Fathers, nor the Fathers the Childrens; but every one ſhall give an account of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and every one ſhall bear his own burden.</p>
               <p>They affirmed, That none could be perfect on this ſide the Grave; and that a Ohilde of God cannot be perfect, as to have no ſinne at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Contrary to the Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. Where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Be ye perfect, as your Heavenly Father is perfect:</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:171845:42"/>And Chriſt doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, nor command impoſſible things; and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We ſpeak wiſdome amongſt them that are perfect,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>And let as many as are perfect be thus minded:</hi> and the Childe of God is perfect, and without ſinne: <hi>for whoſoever is borne of God, doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne, and his ſeed remaines in him, and he cannot ſinne, becauſe be is born of God,</hi> 1 John 3.8, 9. It is as impoſſible for him that is born of God to commit ſinne, as it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him, who is born of the Devil to ceaſe from ſinne.</p>
               <p>They affirmed, That none was Miniſters of Chriſt, but ſuch as wait for an ordinary and mediate call from Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Contrary to the Scripture, which ſaith, <hi>The things of God knowes no man, but the Spirit of God.</hi> And contrary to <hi>Pauls</hi> Call, who ſaith, <hi>Not of man, nor by man, but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> for he neither received of man, neither was he taught it; but it was given to him of God: and this was the Goſpell he preached (Chriſt within, the hope of Glory) and if any bring ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let them be accurſed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1.12. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>They affirmed, That an oath was lawfull to be taken, of men and women.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Contrary to Chriſts Command, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all, &amp;c.</hi> and contrary to the Apoſtles Doctrine, <hi>James</hi> 5.12. who ſaith, <hi>Above all things my Brethren, ſwear not, neither by Heaven, nor by Earth, nor by any other Oath, but let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay, leſt ye fall into Condemnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They affirmed, That Bread and Wine is the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. John,</hi> and the Saints had Communion with God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and their Fellowſhip was in the Light; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if we walk in the Light, as he is in the light, then have we fellowſhip one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 John 1.5, 7. And they who are in the Light have fellowſhip with Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:171845:42"/>every thing in the purity from the Lord; but they that hate the Light, they remain in darkneſſe, and every thing to them is accurſed; to the unbelieving, and diſobedient their is nothing pure, but even their mind and conſcience is defiled.</p>
               <p>They affirmed that ſprinkling Infants is an Ordinance of Chriſt, when as Chriſt never ordained ſuch a thing, and their is no Scripture for it, let the Prieſts of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or any of their brethren in <hi>England</hi> prove it if they can.</p>
               <p>They affirmed, it was lawfull for them be called of men, Maſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Contrary to Chriſt, his expreſſe words in <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8.10. be not ye called of men, Maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They affirmed, Tythes to be lawfull for Miniſters now, ſhewing themſelves to be Antichriſtian, dark, and blind, denying Chriſt Jeſus to be come in the fleſh, and ſaying that is lawful which Chriſt hath diſannulled, and made void, and there is no Law in the new teſtament, that doth allow of Tythes to be paid to a Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, therefore not lawful. Theſe are ſome of the falſe Doctrines and Principles of the Presbyterians about <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> Whereby it was plainly manifeſt that they are guilty of hereſy, and are heriticks, which they would charge upon others; But true Light now ſhineth, which maketh deceipt, and deceivers manifeſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry Foreſide,</hi> ſaid in the hearing of ſeveral people, that Chriſt was not in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Contrary to <hi>Pauls</hi> words in <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. <hi>After it pleaſed God, who ſeparated me from my mothers womb, and called me by his Grace to reveal his Son in me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and in</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>Ye ſeek a proofe of Chriſt ſpeaking in me, and Chriſt in you the hope of Glory, Col.</hi> 1. <hi>and Jeſus Chriſt is in you except ye be reprobates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Kid</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Douglaſſe,</hi> ſaid, to preach that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould walk according to the Light and law within them, is the Doctrine of Devils.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. Paul</hi> and other of the Apoſtles, and Saints,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:171845:43"/>and true Chriſtians, who believed in Chriſt had the Light ſhining in them, and the Law in them, and the Spirit in them, and God and Chriſt dwelt in them, for their bodies were made Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, as the Scriptures declare; and the law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, had made the Apoſtle free from the law of ſin, and death; and ſaith <hi>John,</hi> theſe things I write unto you, that your fellowſhip may be with us, and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt. This was the Doctrine of Chriſt to bring people to Light, Law, life and ſpirit within, to worſhip God in ſpirit; and in truth, and all who draw out, and lead people from this, are deceivers, and their Doctrine is deviliſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Somerwell</hi> Prieſt, ſaid, It was ill manners to to ſay thee and thou to a man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Contrary to the Scripture, which all along doth give thee and thou to a particular, not onely unto man, though never ſo great in the world, but alſo to God himſelf, and unto Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Morton,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Wonſtone,</hi> ſummoned <hi>James Simmonton</hi> to his Seſſions, and being required to prove his Miniſtry, he ſaid; he ſcorned to prove himſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt, Contrary to the Scripture, which ſaith, be ready to give account of the hope that is in you, with meekneſſe, and fear, to every one that ſhall aske you. And when he was told of taking hire for his preaching, contrary to Chriſt his Commiſſion, (who ſaith, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give,</hi>) then the Prieſt aroſe in arage, and called him baſe-born beggarly raskall; contrary to the Apoſtles Doctrine, who ſaith, <hi>Let no corrupt communication come out of your mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Stockdale</hi> being in the Steeple-houſe of <hi>Leſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hagow,</hi> where <hi>John Lum,</hi> Prieſt thereof was preaching; and he being writing ſome of his lyes, the Prieſt cryed out, and ſaid, There was never any ſince the world began was free from ſin, nor never ſhall be: write that ſaid he.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:171845:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Which is quite contrary to plain Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.18, 20, 22. Being made free from ſin, ye became the ſervants of righteouſneſſe; for when ye were the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of ſin, ye were free from righteouſneſſe, but now being made free from ſin, and become ſervants of God, ye have your fruit unto holineſs, and the end, everlaſting life; for the wages of ſin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. The Law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the law of ſin and death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Relation of ſome of the Sufferings of Friends to the Truth in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JOhn Roberton,</hi> called Lord of <hi>Ornock,</hi> publickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to enter <hi>Andrew Hambleton,</hi> in <hi>Shawton-hill,</hi> in his poſſeſſion under him, becauſe he was excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by the Prieſts; Witneſſes of this, <hi>Elexander Hamble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and <hi>John Strudders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Gray, James Findly, John Gray, Robert Smally, John Robine,</hi> was ſummoned to be upon a Jewry at <hi>Dunbarton,</hi> and when they came there, and went with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Barr, they puld off their Bonnets, and bad them ſwear; unto whom they anſwered they would not ſwear, But they will tell the Truth, and take God to be their Witneſſe upon it; but this they would not receive, for <hi>John Callhonne,</hi> called the Sheriffs deputy, bad them ſwear by God, and hold up their hands, or go into priſon: and it was anſwered, we dare not tranſgreſſe the Doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>ſwear not at all;</hi> he ſaid, it was but the Law of Chriſt that bad men not ſwear, but the Law of God bad men ſwear; and ſo would have ſet the old law over Chriſt, who is the end of it, who forbids ſwearing: And becauſe they durſt not tranſgreſſe the Doctrines of Chriſt, in which the Apoſtle lived, who ſaid, Above all things my Bretheren ſwear not at all; they put them all five into Priſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:171845:44"/>
               <head>The Heads of that which paſt in Diſcourſe betwixt the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the two Prieſts of <hi>Hambleton,</hi> in the Prieſts houſe: The Names of the Prieſts are, <hi>Jam. Neſmith,</hi> and <hi>John Engliſh;</hi> in which Diſcourſe they have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted themſelves, and all the reſt of their Generation to be none of the Miniſters of Chriſt, but the Miniſters of Anti-chriſt, who preaches another Goſpel then the Apoſtles did; as in the Diſcourſe following you may plainly ſee. And alſo ſome Reaſons why we deny them.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt. JAmes Neſmith,</hi> ſaid, There is no ſalvation in an ordinarie way for ſinners, without externall Revelation from the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here all may ſee, they hold out another way to ſalvation, then the Prophets and the Apoſtles did; for they ſaid, Chriſt was given for ſalvation to the ends of the earth, <hi>Iſay</hi> 49.6. and there was not ſalvation in any other, nor no other Name given by which any can be ſaved but by the Name of Jeſus, <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.12. But that ſalvation they tell of, which is by external revelation from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, was never held forth by the Prophets, nor the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, nor declared of in all the Scriptures of Truth; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all may ſee they are ſuch as preach another Goſpel then the Apoſtles did, and ſo are to be holden accurſed, and turned away from, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jam. Neſmith</hi> ſaid, That Chriſt doth not excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the knowledge of himſelf, but by the Scriptures, and that the Scripture is the means by which the knowledge of God is imparted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a lye, and Scripture contradiction, For Chriſt, who doth communicate the knowledge of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by his own Spirit ſaith, none knows the Son but the Father, neither doth any man know the Father, but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveal him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:171845:44"/>So it is not by the Scriptures that the true knowledge of God is imparted to any man, but by Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond Prieſt, <hi>John Engliſh.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Firſt, Said, the Vail that was over people in the time of the Law, was the Old Teſtament, and it was taken away by the New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sin was, and is the vail, by which the myſtery was vailed all the time of the Law until now: for when <hi>Moſes</hi> is read, the ſame vail remains over their hearts; for their minds was, and is blinded by the God of this World, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, which is the Image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. nevertheleſs, when their hearts ſhall be turned to the Lord, the vail ſhall be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. which vail is done away in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.14. and not by the Scripture which they call the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and here <hi>John Engliſh</hi> is proved to be a lyar, and of his father the Devil, who is a lyar from the beginning.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>John Engliſh</hi> ſaid, That the Goſpel that was preached to <hi>Abraham,</hi> was the ſame for matter, but not for ſubſtance; neither was it a clear Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Goſpel that was preached to <hi>Abraham,</hi> was the ſame for matter and ſubſtance which <hi>Paul</hi> preached; for matter and ſubſtance is one, and it was a clear Goſpel; for Chriſt the ſubſtance was preached to <hi>Abraham:</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw his day, and rejoyced, <hi>John</hi> 8.56. Therefore give over deceiving the people with lies, and repent.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>John Engliſh</hi> ſaid, The Scripture is the glaſſe by which we ſee the Face of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a lie, and Scripture contradiction; for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God, who commanded the light to ſhine out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, hath ſhined in our hearts, to give the light of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. Mark the Prieſts ignorance or the Scriptures; and here all may ſee that he is one of them that keeps people in darkneſs, from ſeeing the face of God; and erres, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>John Engliſh</hi> ſaid, The foundation of the Prophets and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:171845:45"/>Apoſtles, was meant the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Prophets and Apoſtles meant what they ſpeak, and the ſame foundation which they declared of, and builded upon, did <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Enoch, Noah,</hi> and others who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Faith before the Old and New Teſtament was written, build upon; which foundation was Chriſt, the Rock of Ages, the foundation of the chief Corner Stone, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. But thou art one of them that drawes people from the foundation of the Prophets, and the Apoſtles, to build upon thy lies, and conſequences; which building and foundation the Lord will bring to naught; for he is riſen to ſweep away the refuge of lies, which thou and thy generation hath been covered with, and will make you naked, and bare; for your covering is too ſhort, that your ſhame cannot be hid any longer.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>John Engliſh</hi> ſaid, That they had their commiſſion from <hi>Paul</hi> to give Bread and Wine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here haſt thou made it plainly manifeſt, that thou and thy generation are none of the Miniſters of Chriſt, who ſay you have your Commiſſion from <hi>Paul,</hi> for giving people Bread and Wine: <hi>Paul</hi> never gave ſuch a Commiſſion to any, neither doth he ſay he had power to give any Commiſſion, but declares himſelf a ſervant; neither did <hi>Paul</hi> own any of thy generation of hirelings, which drew people from the true foundation, but declares againſt them, and bids people turn from them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give over deceiving the people, and repent, and call not Bread and Wine any more an Ordinance of God, which thou ſayeſt you are commanded by man to practiſe, leſt thy and their portion be in the Lake, where there is Weeping, and Wailing, and gnaſhing of Teeth, which you cannot eſcape, unleſſe ye Repent; for ye are ſuch as make the Word of God of none effect, by your Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo are to be turned from.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:171845:45"/>
               <head>Reaſons why we deny them, and the Prieſts of their Generation.</head>
               <p>FIRST, They are ſuch teachers as walk in the ſteps of the Phariſees which Chriſt cryed woe againſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.6. They ſtand praying in the Synagogues, and are called of men maſter, contrary to Chriſts command, who ſaid, to his Miniſters, be not ye called of any man, maſter, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſuch as break Chriſts command, therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They are ſuch as preach another Goſpel then the Apoſtles did, and ſaith, Salvation is by the Scripture, which is contrary to that which is held forth by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. Who ſaid Chriſt was given for Salvation to the end of the earth; and the Apoſtle ſaid, their is not ſalvation in any other, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. And becauſe they preach another Goſpel; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, They are ſuch teachers as ſay the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, is the foundation for Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to build upon, which is contrary to the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, who ſaith, Chriſt is the Foundation, and cheif Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Stone, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.22. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.33. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.42. And becauſe they hold out another foundation, then the Holy Men of God did; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, They are ſuch as take hire for their preaching, contrary to Chriſts command, who ſaid to his Miniſtry, Freely ye have received, freely give, and becauſe they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receive freely, nor give freely, therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, They are ſuch teachers, who deny that the Grace of God which brings ſalvation hath appeared unto all men, and ſo would make the Apoſtle a lyar, and a falſe Miniſter, who ſaith, in the 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 11. The Grace of God that brings Salvation hath appeared to all men; and becauſe they deny the Apoſtles Doctrine; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, They are ſuch teachers as deny the Doctrine of perfection, which is the Doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaid, be ye perfect, as your Heavenly Father is perfect; and Holy,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:171845:46"/>for I am Holy; which Doctrine the Apoſtles walked in, and ſpake amongſt thoſe that were perfect, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. And labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to preſent every man in Chriſt Jeſus: and becauſe they are not found in this labour that the Apoſtles was in, to preſent men perfect in Chriſt Jeſus, but cryes againſt it, and preaches up ſin for terme of life, which is the Doctrine of Devils; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Seventh, They are ſuch Teachers as go into <hi>Cains</hi> way, and running greedily after rewards and covetouſneſſe, <hi>Jude</hi> 11. contrary to the Apoſtles, who ſaid, he covered not mans gold, ſilver, nor apparell, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.23. therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Eighth, They are ſuch as are made Miniſters by the will of man, and perſecute, and raile againſt ſuch as fear God, and are of a honeſt converſation; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Nineth, They are ſuch Teachers as adde to, and diminiſh from the Scriptures, unto whom the plagues of God are due; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Tenth, They are ſuch as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> cryes againſt in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. That feed with the fat, and clothe with the wool, and make a prey upon the people; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Eleventh, They are ſuch teachers, as uphold a falſe worſhip in the I dolls Temples made with hands, which Chriſt ſent his Miniſters to cry againſt; and do deny the true worſhip, which is in Spirit and in truth; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <p>Twelfth, They are ſuch Teachers as keepes Drunkards, Swearers, liars, proud, covetous, and all manner of vile perſons in their Aſſemblies, and caſt out them that fear God, and are of honeſt converſation; therefore we deny them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Written by one that Worſhip God in Spirit, and in Truth, and do deny all Falſe Worſhip, which men ſets up; and is alſo a witneſſe for God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all deceit, and deceivers, known by the Name of Will. Stockdale.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>The 26 of the laſt Moneth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Feb.</hi> 1657.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
